<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno III. &amp; IIII. Edvvardi sexti. Actes made in the session of this present parlament, holden vpon prorogation at Westminster, the .iiii daie of Nouembre, in the thirde yere of the reigne of our most dread souuereine Lorde Edward the .vi by the grace of God, king of Englande, Fraunce, and Ireland, defendour of the faith, and of the Churche of Englande, and also of Irelande, in earth the supreme head: and there continued, and kept to the first daie of Februarie, in the .iiii. yere of the reigne of our saied Souuereine Lorde, as foloweth.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Laws, statutes, etc.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07614</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">72799065</idno>
  <idno type="VID">184040</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248534337</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 9430.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S92187</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07614)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184040)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2222:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno III. &amp; IIII. Edvvardi sexti. Actes made in the session of this present parlament, holden vpon prorogation at Westminster, the .iiii daie of Nouembre, in the thirde yere of the reigne of our most dread souuereine Lorde Edward the .vi by the grace of God, king of Englande, Fraunce, and Ireland, defendour of the faith, and of the Churche of Englande, and also of Irelande, in earth the supreme head: and there continued, and kept to the first daie of Februarie, in the .iiii. yere of the reigne of our saied Souuereine Lorde, as foloweth.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Laws, statutes, etc.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], xxxii, [1] leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Richard Graston [i.e. R. Tottell], printer to the Kynges Maiestie.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1553, i.e. 1560?].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The imprint, from colophon, is false; actual printer's name and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Leaves numbered on recto only.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border (Mck. &amp; Ferg. 67), initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁶ E-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Law --  England --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Session laws --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Edward VI, 1547-1553 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184040:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>top: a king or Edward VI seated in the court of parliament, with male figures on both sides; left and right: classical columns or pillars; bottom: two angels or cherubs kneeling beside a tree growing from a barrel</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ANNO. III. &amp; IIII. EDVVARDI SEXTI.</hi> ❧ <hi>ACTES</hi> ❧ made in the Session of this present Parlament, holden vpon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation at Westmynster, the .iiii. daye of Nouembre, in the thirde yere of the reygne of our most dread Souereygne Lorde Edward the .vi. by the grace of God, kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Ireland, defendour of the fayth, and of the Churche of Englande, and also of Irelande, in earth the supreme head: and there continued, and kept to the first daye of Februarye, in the .iiii. yere of the reigne of our sayed Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Lorde, as foloweth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:184040:2"/>
            <head>The table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>AN Acte that the Lorde Chauncellour, or Lorde keper of the great Seale, for the time being, shal name, and appoint the <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> throughout all Shires of Englande according as in time past hath ben accustomed. Chap. i.</item>
               <item>An acte for the true making of Woullen clothes. Chap. ii.</item>
               <item>An acte concerning emprouement of Commons, and Wast groundes. Chap. iii.</item>
               <item>An acte concerning grauntes, and giftes made by patentees, out of lettres patentes. Chap. iiii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the punishmēt of vnlawful assemblies, and rising of the Kinges Subiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Chap. v.</item>
               <item>An acte, concerning the repeale of a braunche in the acte of parlament made for buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of tanned Leather. Chap. vi.</item>
               <item>An acte for the repeale of a Statute made in the .xxv. yere of king Hēry the .viii. tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the takyng of wyld foule at certayne times of the yere. Chap. vii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the continuaunce of the Statute of Sewers. Chap. viii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the buying of rawe hydes, and calf skinnes. Chap. ix.</item>
               <item>An acte for the abolishing, &amp; putting away of diuers bookes, &amp; ymages. Chap. x.</item>
               <item>An acte that the kinges Maiestie may nominate, and appoynct .xxxii. persons to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use, and make Ecclesiasticall lawes. Chap. xi.</item>
               <item>An acte for the ordryng of Ecclesiasticall ministers. Chap. xii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the restitutiō in bloud of Syr William Sharington knight. Chap. xiii</item>
               <item>An acte for the restitucion in bloud of Marye Seymour daughter to Syr Thomas Seymour knyght, Lorde Seymour of Sudleye, late Admirall of Englande. Chap. xiiii.</item>
               <item>An acte against fonde, and phantasticall prophecies Chap. xv.</item>
               <item>An acte touching the punishment of vagabondes, &amp; other idle persones. Chap. xvi.</item>
               <item>An acte agaynst vnlawfull hunting in any Parke, Forrest, Chase, or other enclosed grounde. Chap. xvii.</item>
               <item>An acte concerning Fee fermes, mencioned in the last Session. Chap. xviii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the buying of rother beastes, and cattall. Chap. xix</item>
               <item>An acte touching the repeale of a certayne braūche of an acte passed in the last Sessiō of this Parlament, cōcerning victuallers, and artificers. Chap. xx.</item>
               <item>An acte for the buying, and sellyng of butter, and chese. Chap. xxi.</item>
               <item>An acte touching the reteyning of iourneymen, by dyuers persons. Chap. xxii.</item>
               <item>An acte concerning the release of the branches in the last act of relief, for the paye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of Shepe, and Clothes, and also a graunte of a Subsidie to be paied in one yere. Chap. xxiii.</item>
               <item>An acte of the kinges maiesties most free, and generall perdone. Chap. xxiiii.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:184040:2"/>
            <head>¶ An Acte, that the Lorde Chauncellour, or Lorde keeper of the great seale for the tyme beyng, shall name and appoynct the <hi>Custos rotulorum</hi> throughout all shyres of England, according as in time past hath been accustomed. ¶ The first Chapitre.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parlament holden at west<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynster in the .xxxvii. yere of the reigne of the most excellent prynce of famouse memorye kyng Henrye the .viii. it was enacted that no persone, or persones, shoulde from the makyng of the sayed act be nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, and appoynted to thoffice, or offices of the <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> within any shyre of this realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, Wales, or other the kynges dominions, marches, or territories of the same, but suche as shoulde haue a byll signed with the Kinges hande for the same, whiche byll sygned, shoulde bee a sufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt by aucthoritie of the sayed act, to the Lord Chauncelour of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and Lorde keeper of the great seale, for the tyme beyng, to make from tyme to tyme, commyssion or commissions, assygnyng, and auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorising therby, the same person to be <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> vntill the kyng had by another byll assigned with his owne hand appoynted, &amp; ordeyned an other persone, to haue, occupie, and exercyse the same office of <hi>Custos rotulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and that the sayed persone appoynted, and assygned to be <hi>Custos rotulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> as is abouesaid, should, &amp; might occupie, exercise, end enioye the sayd office of <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> by him selfe, or by hys sufficient deputie learned in the lawes of thys realme, &amp; meete, and hable to supplye the sayed office, accordyng to the tenour of the sayed graunt, or cōmission, as by the same act emong other thinges more at large it doth, and may appere. Sence the making of which statute, diuerse &amp; many persons being in the sayed offices of <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> in diuers shires of the realme, haue departed this present lyfe, and dyed, so that there hath not come to the handes of the chauncelour of England, or Lord keeper of the great seale, anye byll, or billes assigned with the kinges maiesties hand for the naming, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or assigning of any newe <hi>Custos rotulorum</hi> in the same shyres, the sayed offices haue remayned voyde for a long tyme, to the great let of Iustice. And also for that it shalbe very tedious, and muche to the molestyng of the Kynges Maiestie vpon euery auoydaunce of suche <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> by death, or otherwyse, to moue his Maiestie for the signyng of bylles for other persons to be elected, named, chosen, and appoynted to supplye the sayed offices of <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> being voyde. And for that the nomination and appointing of the sayed office of <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> long tyme before the
<pb facs="tcp:184040:3"/> makyng of the sayed Statute last before rehearsed dyd apperteyne, and belong to the office of the Chauncellour of Englande, or Lorde keeper of the great seale for the tyme being: Be it therfore enacted by the kyng our souereygne Lorde, with the assent of the Lordes spirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and the Commons in this present parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same: that the Chauncellour of Englande, or lorde keper of the great seale, for the tyme being, shall at all tyme, and tymes herafter, and from time to time, without any bill, or billes to be assigned with the kinges hande, name, elect, assigne, and appoynct such person, &amp; persons to be <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> within euerye shyre of thys realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, Wales, and other the kinges dominiōs, Marches, &amp; territories of the same, or by anye of them, as by the dyscrecion of the sayed Lorde Chauncellour, or Lorde keeper of the great seale, for the tyme beyng, shalbe thought hable, and meete to haue and exercise the same. And that the sayed persone, and persones, so to be appoincted, elected, named, and assygned by the sayed Lord Chauncellour, or Lord keeper of the great Seale for the tyme beyng, shall, and may occupie, exercise, and enioye the same office of <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> by hym selfe, or by his sufficient depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or deputies, in as ample, and large maner, and fourme, as if the saied acte had neuer been had ne made, the before rehearsed acte, or anye thing theryn conteyned to the contrarye herof in anye wyse notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alway, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayed, that all such as now haue any of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayed offices of <hi>Custos rotulorum,</hi> by the kinges letters patentes, or commission, to thē, or any of them made, shall, &amp; may enioy, haue, and exercise theyr sayed offices by vertue of the same letters patentes, or commission, by him selfe, or his sufficient, and hable deputie, instructed in the lawes of this realme, any thing in this presēt acte, had, or made to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouyded also that it be enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayed, that the Archebishop of Yorke, the byshop of Durham, the byshop of Ely, and euery of theyr successours, the Chauncelour of the Duchie of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster for the tyme beyng, and all, and euery person, and persons, corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and bodies corporated, to whom the kinges maiestie, or anye of hys noble progenitours by hys, or theyr letters patentes, or Acte of parlament, haue geuen, and graunted anye libertie and aucthoritie, or otherwyse haue aucthoritie by other lawfull meanes, or wayes, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne, make, &amp; constitute, any of the sayed officers of <hi>Custos rotulorum</hi> within anye countie palantine, or other place, shall, and maye haue, and enioye the same libertie, &amp; aucthoritie, according as they haue had, and enioied the same, any thing in this presēt act, had, or made, to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .ii. Chapitre. ¶ An Acte for the true making of woullen clothes.</head>
            <pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:184040:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche as by the sleighte, and subtile making of Clothes, and colours, within dyuers partes of thys realme, now of late practised, &amp; vsed, not onely great infamies &amp; slaundres hath growē to the same realme but also the kinges maiesties faithfull, and true sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iettes haue susteyned great losse in the vse, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the same clothes, so sleightly, &amp; subtily made. For remedye, and reformacion wherof: bee it ordeyned, &amp; enacted by the kinges most excellent maiestie, with thassent of the Lordes spirituall, &amp; temporall, and the cōmons in this present parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that euerye Clothter, and Clothmaker, shall from the feast of the annunciation of our Ladie next commyng, set hys Seale of Leade to his Cloth, declaring therby the iust lengthes therof to be tryed by the water. And that no persone shall from the sayed feaste streygne, or stretche any set clothes, or any other cloth, aboue one yarde and a di. in length, and a quarter of a yarde in breadth, vpon peyne to forfetct .xl. s. for euery defaut. And that no person, nor persones, shall frō the sayed feast, vpon peyne last before remembred, put to sale any cloth, which when it shalbe wet, shall shrinke more then .i. yarde &amp;. di. in all the length, and a quarter of a yard in the breadth. And that narrow streites, and kerseyes, shall not from the saied feast be stretched, aboue a yarde in length, and di a {quam}. of a yarde in breadth, vpon the peyne for euerye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault therin .xx. s. nor shall put to sale ane cloth, narrow, streyte, or kersey the pieces wherof being wet, shall shrinke more then after the same seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rates in the whole piece, vpon peyne to forfeycte for euerye suche of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence .xx. s. And further, that no persone, or persones, occupyeng the feate of dyeng, shall dye, or alter into colours, or cause to be died, or altred into colours, any wollen clothes, as browne blewes, picukes, tawnies, or violettes, except the same wollen clothes be perfectly boyled, greyned or madered vpon the woade, and shot with good, and sufficient corke, or orchal after a due, substanciall, &amp; sufficient maner of workemanshyp, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thauncient workmanship in time past vsed, vpon peyne for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery default to forfeyt .xx. s. nor that any person shall from the sayed feast dye any woll to be cōuerted into cloth called russettes, mustres, marbles, grayes, royes, &amp; such lyke colours, or to be conuerted, &amp; made into hattes or cappes, onles the same woll be perfectlye woaded, boyled, and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred according to the true, &amp; auncient vsage, vpon the peine of forfeyture for the false dyeng of euery such cloth, or of asmuch wolle, as shall serue for the makyng of euery cloth contrary to the true meanyng therof .xl. s. Nor shall dye with brasell to thintent to make a false colour in cloth nor wolle hattes, nor cappes, vpon peyne for euery default to forfeyt .xx. s.</p>
            <p>And that no person, or persones, shall after the sayed feast put any floc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, chalke, flowre, or sterche, or any other deceiuable thyng, vpō any set clothe, or vpon any other cloth, or clothes coloured, or vncoloured, vpon
<pb facs="tcp:184040:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:184040:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:184040:5"/> peyne to forfeycte for euery suche offence .xl.s. And that no persone shall from the sayed feast, occupie any yron cardes, or pickardes in rowing of any set cloth, or any maner of wollen cloth, vpon peyne to forfeyt aswell the sayed yron cardes, or pickardes, as also the summe of .xx.s. for euery such offence. Nor that any persone shall from the saied feast sell any cloth by any lesse measure then after the true content therof, to be moten and measured by the yarde, adding to euery yarde, one inche of the rule, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the statute made in the .vi. yeare of the reygne of the most worthy prince of most famous memory kyng Henry the .viii. Father vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our souereigne Lorde the kyng that nowe is, vpon peyne to forfeycte for euerye yarde of cloth so put to sale, by anye other lesse measure .vi.s. viii.d. And that no persone shall from the sayd feast, put to sale here with in the realme, eyther by retayle, or otherwise, any cloth beyng pressed to be occupied, and worne here within the realme of Englande, Wales, or Irelande, vpon peyne of forfeyture of the same cloth, or the value therof that haue been so pressed, and put to sale as is last before remembred.</p>
            <p>And for the better executing of thys statute: be it enacted by thaucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie aforesaied, that in euery toune, village, or Hamlet, being not corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, where anye cloth shalbe made, or solde, the Iustice of peace of the same shyre where any such toune, vyllage, or hamlet is, or two of them at the least, and in euery citie, borough, or toune corporate, the head officer, or officers of euerye the same citie, borough, or toune corporate together with the wardens of the clothworkers, or two of them at the least, shall haue full power, and aucthoritie, by vertue of this acte, once euerye yere to conuent, and call before them by theyr precept, or otherwyse .ii. iiii. vi. viii. or more, as they shall thinke good by theyr discrecion, of the most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, discrete, &amp; indifferēt men of euery such citie, borough, toune, village, or hamlet, where any cloth shalbe made, or sold, &amp; thē shall cōstitute, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne, and appoynt to be ouerseers for one whole yere then next folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within the citie, borough, toune, village, or hamlet, where the same ouerseers shalbe dwelling, charging them also vpon theyr othes, and as they doe tender thonor of the realme, and the cōmon wealth of the same, that they doe endeuour them selues for that yere, asmuch as in them shal lye to see that this statute be truely obserued, and kept within the limites of theyr charge, in euerye part therof. And that the same ouerseers, or .ii. of them, shall euery quarter of the saied yere at the least, or so oftē as nede shal require by their discrecions, by force herof, visite, and goe into euery clothiers, drapers, cloth workers, diers, and pressors houses, shoppes, &amp; other places, where cloth, or died woll shalbe, &amp; there to make due search &amp; to view the clothes, and wolles, made, or dyed, or remaining to be sold and to serche and trye, aswell whether the sayed clothes, be drawen, or streigned, or falsly dyed, as also of all other the defaultes before specified, commytted, or doen, contrarye to the true meanyng of thys acte. And if vpon the serche, the clothes be founde drawen, or streyned, or the cloth, or
<pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:184040:5"/> wolles falsly dyed, or coloured, or any other of the sayed faultes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or doen contrary to the true meanyng of thys statute: That then the saied seuerall forfeytures to encurre vpon the partie, or parties, whiche shall offende in the same, or in any of them: thone halfe of all whiche for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faitures to be vnto the king our Souereygne Lorde, hys heyres, or suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours, and thother halfe to such of the sayed ouerseers, as doeth fynde the saied defautes, or causes of forfaitures, and that will sue for the same in any of the kynges courtes of recorde, or before the Iustices of peace, within any such citie, borough, or toune corporate, or before the Iustices of peace within any shyre where anye suche forfeitures shalbe had out of any citie or towne corporate, the same suite to be pursued by byll, plaint, action of debt, information, or otherwyse, and in whiche suite, no wager of lawe, essoine, or protection shalbe allowed for the defendaunt. And if the sayed ouerseers shalbe negligent, and will not sue for the same forfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, by the space of one halfe yere next after the cause of the same for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faitures committed, &amp; doen, that then thone halfe of the same forfayture to be vnto our sayed Soueraygne Lorde the kyng, his heyres, or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours, and the other halfe to hym whiche will sue for the same, as is aforesayed, within one other halfe yere next after such default be had by the saied ouerseers. And if any of the sayed persones so commaunded to appeare to be made ouerseers, as is aforesayed, &amp; hauing no reasonable excuse, doe refuse to come, &amp; to take vpō him, or them to be an ouerseer, as is aforesaied, that then euery such persone refusing, &amp; hauing no reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excuse so to doe, to forfaicte for euerye suche refusing .xl.s. thone halfe therof to be to the kyng our sayed Souereygne, hys heyres, or succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours, and the other halfe to the Iustices of peace, or other head officer, or Officers, by whose commaundement he was commaunded to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, or to be an ouerseer, and the same ouerseer so offending, to remain in the warde of the Sherife, vntyll suche tyme, as he had made paye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the sayed forfaicture, or otherwise put in sufficient bonde for the satisfaction of the same. And if the same ouerseers, or two of them at the leaste, doe not once euery quarter of the yeare, make due searche for the true executing of thys statute: that then euery of the sayed ouerseers, to forfaycte for euerye suche defaulte .x.li. thone halfe to be to the Kynges highnesse, hys heyres, or successours, and the other halfe to him that will sue for the same by byll, playnt, accion of debt, information, or otherwise. In whiche suite, no essoyne, or protection shalbe allowed for the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunt. And if the sayed ouerseers shalbe interrupted, and not suffred to entre into the saied houses, shoppes, or other places, where any such clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, or wolles shalbe made, or died, or any other of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayd defaultes shal happen to be doen, or commytted, there to make searche for the better executyng of thys Statute, that then euery one that so shall make anye suche interruption, shal forfeycte .xx.l. the one half of whiche forfeicture to be to oure sayd Souereigne Lord the kyng, hys heires, or successours,
<pb facs="tcp:184040:6"/> and thother halfe therof to be to the sayed ouerseers, to whome any such interruption shalbe made, and the same to be obteyned, and pursued for, in such maner, and fourme, as before in thys acte is expressed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie of other of the sayed forfeyctures.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwaies, &amp; be it enacted by thauctoritie aforesayed, that it shall, &amp; may be lefull to euery person, and persons, to put to sale any cloth or clothes, made, dyed, or prest, whiche before the sayed feast of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of our Ladie shalbe made, dyed, or prest, at anye tyme within one yere, next after the sayed feast of the Annunciation of our Ladye, so as the Alnager, or his deputie, or other head officer in anye suche citie, Borough, Towne, Village, or hamlet, doe put some notorious marke to euery such cloth, wherby the same may be knowen to be made before the sayed feast of the Purification of our Lady next commyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded also, that no maner of person, shall take any aduauntage of any of the sayed forfeictures, by reason of thys Statute, onlesse the same persone doeth cōmence his suite, within one yere next after the sayed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and forfeictures committed.</p>
            <p>And to thentent, that all suche clothes as shalbe made within thys Realme, or any other of the kynges dominions after the said feast shalbe the better knowen from the other clothes made before the same time: Be it therfore enacted by thaucthoritie afore saied, that euery Clothier shall before such time, as he shall putte his cloth to sale, being made after the sayed feast, cause euerye cloth to be marked with a lettre of <hi>E.</hi> crowned, wrought in the cloth, vpon peyne of forfeycture for euerye cloth so beyng solde, and not marked with the sayed lettre <hi>E.</hi> by anye such clothier .xx.s. the one halfe of whiche forfaycture to bee to our soueraygne Lorde the king, his heyres, or successours, and thother half to hym that will sue for the same in maner, and fourme before rehearsed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .iii. Chapter. ¶ An Acte concerning the improuementes of commons, and wast groundes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parlament holden at Marton in the .xx. yere of the reygne of king Henrye the third, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined that forbecause many great men of Englande which had enfeoffed Knyghtes, &amp; other their free te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes of small tenements in theyr great manours dyd complayne that they myght not make theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> residue of theyr manours, as of wast woddes and pastures, where the same feoffees had sufficient pasture, as muche as belōged vnto theyr tenemētes, it was prouided &amp; graūted, that what soeuer persons so enfeoffed, brought assyse of <hi>nouel disseison,</hi> of theyr cōmon of pasture, &amp; before the iustices it were recognised, that they had asmuch pasture as dyd suffise vnto theyr tenementes, and that they had free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse,
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:184040:6"/> and egresse into, &amp; from their tenemētes vnto theyr pasture, that then they should therwith be contented, and that they, vpon whome they had complayned, should depart quiete with that, that they myght make theyr profite of theyr landes, wastes, woddes, and pastures. And if it were sayed that they had not sufficient pasture, or sufficient ingresse, and egresse, asmuch as doth belong vnto theyr tenemētes, as is abouesaied, that then the trueth therof shoulde be enquired by Assyse: and if it were recognised by the Assyse, that theyr ingresse, &amp; egresse were in any thyng letted by the same deforciatours, or that they had not sufficient pasture and sufficient ingresse, &amp; egresse, as is aboue saied, that then they shoulde recouer theyr <hi>seison</hi> by viewe of the iurours, so that by the dyscrecion, and othe of them, the complaynantes should haue sufficient pasture, and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ingresse, and egresse, in fourme afore sayed, &amp; that the dysseisours shoulde be in amerciament of the kyng, and shoulde yelde damages, as they were wont to doe before the same prouision. And if it were recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the assise, that the complainauntes had sufficient pasture with free ingresse, and egresse, as is aboue mencioned, that then the other myght lawfully doe theyr profite of the residue, and shoulde goe quyte from the same assise, as in the sayed estatute more plainly appeareth.</p>
            <p>And where also in the parlament holden at Westminster, after Eas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the .xiii. yere of the reygne of king Edward the fyrst, it was ordeined that where in the statute made at Marton, it was agreed, that lordes of wastes, woddes, and pastures, myght approue them selues of theyr wastes, woddes, and pastures, notwithstandyng the gaynesaying, and contradiction of theyr tenauntes, whyles the same tenauntes had suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient pasture to theyr tenementes, with free ingresse, and egresse, into, &amp; from the same. And for that no mencion was made betwene neighbour and neighbour, manye Lordes of wastes, woddes, and pastures, vnto that time were let by contradiction, or gaynsaying of neyghbours, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng sufficient pasture. And forasmuche as foreyn tenauntes haue no greater right of commoning in the wood, wast, or pasture of any Lorde then the propre tenantes of the same lorde, it was from thencefourth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned, that the sayed Statute prouyded at Marton, betwene the lord and his tenauntes, should haue place from thenceforth betwene the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of wastes, woddes, and pastures, and neighbours, sauing sufficient pasture to theyr men, and neyghbours, so that the Lordes of the same wast, wastes, woddes and pastures maye approue them selues of the residue, and that the same shoulde be obserued of them that claime pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as perteinyng to theyr tenauntes. But if anye manne clayme com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of pasture by speciall feoffement or graunt, to a certeyne numbre of beastes, or otherwyse, then of common right he ought to haue it. Where couenaunt doeth abrogate the lawe, he shall haue suche recouerie, as he ought to haue by fourme of the graunt to him made. And that by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a Windmyll, shepehouse, dairye, augmentation, or encrease of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye court necessarye, or curtilage, from thencefourth, no man should be
<pb facs="tcp:184040:7"/> greued by assise of <hi>nouel disseison,</hi> of common of pasture. And for as much as it happeneth sometyme that some men hauyng right to approue to hym selfe, hath made, or leuied a diche, or a hedge, &amp; other by night, or such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tyme, when they beleue theyr deede should not be knowen, dooe, or will cast downe the same diche, or hedge, and that it cannot bee knowen by veredite of assise, or iurie, who dyd cast down the same diche or hedge nor the men of the next towne wil endicte them that be gyltie of the same deedes, then the next towneshyp adioigning about the same shalbe des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treigned to leuie, and make vp the same diche, or hedge, at theyr propre costes, and to yelde dammages, as in the sayed estatute emongest other thynges more playnly appereth.</p>
            <p>And forasmuche as the aforesayed estatutes been thought benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for the common wealth of thys realme of Englande. Be it enacted by the kyng our Souereygne Lorde, with the assent of the Lordes spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and temporall, and the commons in thys present parlament as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that all and euery the sayed Statutes, and all braunches, clauses, articles, sentences, matters, and poynctes conteyned, and specifyed in them, and euery of them, nowe not repealed, shall from hencefourth be good, and effectuall, and also stand, and be in their full strength, force, and effect.</p>
            <p>And because that such persones as shall bryng assise of <hi>nouel disseison</hi> vpon the sayed estatutes, or vpon any of them, shall by force of the same estatute, recouer but onely single dammages, whiche is thought to bee a small recompence for the same. Therfore be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesayed, that such person, and persones, as shall at anye tyme hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bring assise vpon any braunche, or article of the saied estatutes, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, and haue iudgement to recouer, shall haue his, or their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages trebled by the iudgement of the court, where such assise, &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment shalbe had.</p>
            <p>And where in dyuers countreies of thys Realme, there hath bene builded vpon Commons, or wast groundes, certayne necessary houses with grounde, vnder the quantitie of three acres, and not aboue three acres, enclosed to, and with the same, and in some place there is enclosed a garden, orchard, or pond, out, of, or in such wastes, or groundes, which excede not the quantitie of two acres, or theraboutes, whiche doeth no hurt, and yet is much commoditie to the owner therof, and to others: be it therfore enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayed, that the sayed two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer actes, nor any of them, nor any thing in thē conteyned, shall extende to any such house, ground, or other thing so enclosed, as is last herin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mencioned, ne shall cause any person or persones, to lose, or forfayte any peyne, damage or penaltie for the same.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and bee it enacted, that if anye suche house hath been hertofore buylded vpon anye suche wast grounde, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sayed, and that there be aboue the numbre of three acres enclosed to the
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:184040:7"/> same, that then the sayed house, and three acres parcell of the same en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure, shall still remayne, stande, abyde, and continue in lyke, and the same fourme, and degree, as it nowe doeth, and that the ouerplus of the sayed three acres so enclosed, as is aforesaied, shall, and may be layed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by thowner, or owners of the same wastes, anye thyng in this acte, or in any of the sayed former actes, to the contrary in any wyse notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .iiii. Chapitre. ¶ An Acte concernyng grauntes, and gyftes made by patentees out of letters patentes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the ryght noble, and famouse king of full wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy memorie kyng Henry the .viii. father to our most dread, and nowe naturall Souereygne liege Lord, sithens the fowerth daye of Februarye in the .xxvii. yere of his late reygne, and also the kinges most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maiestie, by theyr seuerall letters patentes haue geuen, graunted, bargained, solde, and exchaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to, and with dyuerse and sundry the subiectes of this realme, bodies politique, and corporate in fee simple, fee taile, for terme of lyfe, or yeres, diuers honours, castles, manours, landes, tenementes, and other here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditamentes, and offices: After, &amp; since which grauntes, bargaines, sales, and exchaunges, diuerse of the saied patentees, theyr heires, successours, or assignes, haue bargained, solde, geuen, exchaūged, or dimised diuerse particuler partes, parcels, or portions of the saied honours, castles, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, lādes, tenemētes, hereditamētes, &amp; offices, or other thinges ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appertaining, or belōging to other persone, or persones, bodies po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, or corporate, that is to saye, to some of thē in fee simple, to some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in fee taile, for terme of life, or yeres, or otherwise. And after the same patentees for cōsiderations them mouing, haue surrendred, or geuen vp theyr saied lettres patētes into the Chauncerie, or otherwise the same let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres patentes haue been forfaited by attaindre, lost, cancelled, embesiled, or by other waies or meanes haue come to the handes of the kinges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie hys late father. And therupon oft tymes the enrollemēt of the same hath been made voyde, and frustrate, sometime in part, and sometime in the whole, by reason wherof, suche persones, bodies politique, or corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, as haue had interest or tytle, in, or to the same Castles, manours, or particuler portiones, or parcelles of the same so to them geuen, and graunted, haue been in tymes past, and in tyme to come are lyke to be dysherited, or in daunger of losse of theyr interest, in, or to the same, to theyr no litle hynderaunce, and peryl: For remedie wherof, be it ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, establyshed, and enacted by thaucthoritie of this present parlament
<pb facs="tcp:184040:8"/> that all &amp; euery person or persones, bodies politique, or corporate, which lawfullye shall, or maye clayme by force of any patent, or patentes made sithens the fowerth daye of Februarye, or hereafter to be made by the kynges maiestie, hys heyres or successours, kynges of thys realme, or by any of them, and all other that nowe haue, or hereafter shall happen to haue anye good or lawfull estate, ryght, tytle, rent, profeicte, interest, or possession, of, in, to, or out of any honours, manours, landes, tenemētes, hereditamentes, or offices, or of other thynges, to anye of the premys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, apperteynyng or belongyng, or to anye part, parcell, or membre of them, or anye of them, by, from, or vnder anye such patent, or patentes, or any of them, or by, from, or vnder the heyres, successours, or assignes of them, or anye of them, or by, from, or vnder the state of anye others, whiche had, haue, or hereafter shall haue the state, tytle, or interest, of anye suche patentee, or patentees, or by any other meanes vnder the date of suche letters patentes, shall, and maye at all tymes hereafter, in anye the kynges courtes, hys heyres, or successours, and els where, by vertue of thys present acte, make, and conueygh vnto them selfe tytle by waye of declaration, playnt, auowrie, tytle, barre, or otherwyse, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well agaynst the kynges highnesse, his heyres, &amp; successours, and euery of them, as agaynst anye other persone, or persones, vnto the sayed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, castles, manours, landes, tenementes, offices, and other the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses, or any part, or parcell of the same, vnto them, or any theyr prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours, or auncestours, or others, whose estate they haue in the same, by, frō, or vnder the said patentes, or any of thē, or theyres, auncestours, or assygnes of anye of them, or otherwise, vnder the date of the sayed let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres patentes, comprised, &amp; conteyned in any exemplification, or constat therof made, or to be made, by the shewing fourth of the saied exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or constat of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rolle, or of so much therof, as shall serue for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in variance, vnder the great seale of Englande. And the same exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification, or constat of the saied enrollement so (as is aforesayed) plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and shewed, shalbe of lyke, &amp; the same force, and effect, to all entētes, &amp; cōstructions in the lawe, as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied fyrst lettres patentes were, &amp; should be of, if the same were, or should be pleaded, or shewed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .v. Chapitre. ¶ An Acte for the punishment of vnlawfull assemblies, and rysing of the kinges subiectes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche, as it is most necessary in a common we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alth to prouyde that tranquillitie, and peace maye be continued in this realme, and that all thinges being cōtrary therunto, may by foresight be eschewed: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ordeyned, and enacted, by the king our so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne Lorde, with the assent of the Lordes, and Communes, of thys presente Parlamente assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that if
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:184040:8"/> anye persones, to the numbre of .xii. or aboue, beyng assembled together at any tyme, after the .xii. daye of February next commyng, shall intende, goe about, practise, or put in vre, with force of armes, vnlawfully, and of theyr awne aucthoritie, to murdre, kill, slaye, take, or imprison, any of the Kynges most honourable priueye counsaile, or vnlawfullye to alter or chaunge anye lawes, made, or establyshed for Religion, by aucthoritie of Parlament, or any other lawes or estatutes of thys realme, or anye of them. The same number of .xii. or aboue, being commaūded or requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by the Shirife of the Shyre, or by any Iustice of peace of the same Shyre, or by the Maior, Shirifes, Iustices of peace, or Baylyfes, of any citie, borough, or towne corporate, where any such assemblie shalbe vnlawfullye had, or made, by Proclamacion in the kynges name, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre, &amp; repayre to theyr awne houses, habitacions, or places from whēce they came, and they or any of them, notwithstanding suche Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, shall remayne, or make theyr abode, or continue together, by the space of an whole houre, after suche commaundement or request, made by Proclamacion, or after that shall willyngly, in forceable and ryotous maner attempt to doe, or putte in vre, anye the thynges aboue specifyed: That then aswell euery suche abode or continuyng together, as euerye suche acte or offence, that after suche Proclamacion, commaundement, or request had or made, shalbe attempted to be doen, practised, or put in vre by any persones, being of the numbre aforesaied, shalbe iudged high treason, in all and singuler those persons, that so shall make theyr abode, or continue together, or shall attempt or commyt any suche acte, and the offendours therin, theyr aydours, abbettours, and procurers, to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged Traytours to the Kyng and the realme, and shall suffre execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of death, as in case of hygh treason.</p>
            <p>And ferthermore, be it enacted, ordeyned, and establyshed, by thauc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie aforesayed, that if any persones, to the sayed numbre of .xii. or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, after the sayed .xii. daye of February, shall intende, goe about, prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, or put in vre, in maner and fourme aforesayed, to ouerthrowe, cutte, breake, cast downe, or dygge vp the pales, hedges, dytches, or other clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of anye Parkes, Parke, or other groundes, or grounde enclosed, or the bankes of any fyshe ponde or poole, or anye Conduictes for water, Cōduite headdes, or Conduite pipes, hauing course of water, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that the same, or any of them, frō thencefurth should remayne open, not inclosed or voyde, or vnlawfully to haue cōmon, or waye in the saied Parkes, Parke, or other groundes, or grounde inclosed, or in anye of them, or to destroye the Dere, in any maner of Parkes or Parke, or any Warreins or Warrein of Conies, or any Douehouses, or anye fishe in any ponde or poole, or to pull or cut downe, any houses, barnes, mylles, or Bayes, or to burne anye stackes of corne or grayne, or to abate, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falke or diminyshe the rentes or yerelye value of any Manours, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or tenementes, or the pryce of anye victuall, Corne, or Grayne, or
<pb facs="tcp:184040:9"/> any other thing, vsuall for the sustenaunce of men: and beyng required or cōmaunded, by any Iustice of peace, or by the Shirife of the countie, or by the Maior, Bailife, or Bailifes, or other head officers of any head citie, or towne corporate, where such assemblie shalbe had, by proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion to be made in the kynges name, to retyre or retourne, in peaceable maner to theyr habitacions, places, and houses, from whēce they came, and they, or any of them, notwithstanding such Proclamacion, shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne or make theyr abode, or cōtinue together, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> space of one whole houre, after such commaundement, or request made by proclamacion, or after that shall in forcible maner attempt to doe, or put in vre anye of the thinges last before mencioned: That then aswell euery such abode, or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing together, as euery such acte, that after such proclamacion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maūdement, or request, had or made, shalbe doen, practised, or put in vre, by any persones, being aboue the numbre of .xii. shalbe adiudged felony, and the offendours therin to be adiudged felons, and shall suffre execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of death, as in case of felony, and euery of the same persones, to lose the benefite of his clergie, and Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>And also it is ordeyned and enacted by the aucthoritie aboue sayed, that if anye persone or persones, after the sayed .xii. day of February, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully, and without aucthoritie, by ringyng of any bell, or belles, soū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any Dromme, Trompet, Horne, or other instrument whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, or by fyering of any Beacon, or by malicious speaking, or vtteryng of any wordes, or making any outcrye, or by setting vp, or casting of any bylles, byll, or wryting whatsoeuer, or by any other deede, or acte, shall rayse, or cause to be raysed, or assembled anye persones, to the numbre of twelue or aboue, to thintent that the same persones should doe, commit, and put in vre, anye of the actes, or thinges aboue mencioned, and that the persones, to the number of .xii. or aboue, so raysed and assembled, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter request or commaundement, had or geuen, in fourme afore saied, shal make theyr abode, or continue together, as is aforesaied, or vnlawfullye perpetrate, doe, commit, or put in vre, any of the actes, or thynges aboue saied: that then all and singuler persones, by whose speaking, dede, acte, or any other the meanes aboue specifyed, any persones to the numbre of twelue or aboue, shalbe reysed or assembled for the doing, committing, or putting in vre, anye of the actes, or thinges aboue mencioned, shalbe adiudged for hys so speakyng, or doyng, a felon, and shall suffre executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of death, as in case of felonye, and shall lose hys benefite, and Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary, and Clergie.</p>
            <p>And ouer that, it is ordeyned and enacted by the aucthoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayed, that if any persones, to the numbre of .xl. and aboue, after the saied xii. daye of Februarye, shalbe assembled together, in forcible maner vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully, and of their owne auctoritie, to thyntent to doe, exercyse, or put in vre, any of the thinges aboue mencioned, or to doe anye other tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous, Felonious, or Rebellious acte, or actes, and so shall continue by
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:184040:9"/> the space of two houres, that then euery persone, so beyng willingly as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, in forcible maner &amp; so continuing, by the space of two houres, shalbe adiudged a traytour to the kynge, and to the realme, and shall suffre execucion of death as in case of hygh treason.</p>
            <p>And also, that if any wyfe or seruan̄t of any of the same persones, or any other persone whatsoeuer, shall willingly, and without compulsion bring, send, deliuer, or conueigh any money, harneis, artillery, weapon, meate, bread, drinke, or other victuall, to any person, or persones, so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing assembled as is afore saied, during suche tyme, as he or they shall so be assembled, or bee together, as is afore saied: that then euery wyfe ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, or other persone so bringyng, sendyng, deliuering, or conueyghing any money, harneys, artillery, weapon, meate, bread, drinke, or victuall, to the same persones, so beyng assembled together, in forcible maner, or to any of them, shalbe iudged a traytour to the kyng, and to the realme, and shall suffre execution of death, as in case of hygh treason.</p>
            <p>And ferthermore it is ordeyned and enacted, by the auctoritie aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayed, that euery persone, that at any tyme herafter shalbe attaynted, of or for, any of the treasons, or treason aboue mencioned, shall vpon hys sayed attayndour, forfeycte hys goodes, Cattals, interestes, for terme of lyfe, and of yeres, landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes, in lyke maner and fourme, as anye persone ateaynted of Felonye, onelye should, or ought to forfeycte, by the common lawes of thys realme, and not otherwise: that is to say, the kyng to haue the yere, and day, &amp; waste of suche Landes and Tenementes, wherof any persone so attaynted, shall at the tyme of the treason committed, or at any tyme after, haue an estate of fee symple, and also the gooddes and Cattals, reall and perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. And that the Lordes, of whom, the sayed landes, and tenementes, or any part therof shalbe holden, to haue and enioye the landes and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes, holden of hym or them for euer, in such the same maner and fourme, as in cases of attaindour of Felonie, at the common lawe. And that euery persone, that at any time hereafter shalbe attaynted, of anye of the Treasons aforesaied, shall forfeict the Landes and Tenementes, and other hereditamentes, wherof he shalbe seazed, of any state in taile, or for terme of lyfe or lyues, at the tyme of any such Treason commyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or at any time after, duryng hys lyfe onely, and no lenger, onlesse the persone so attaynted, shalbe therof seazed in hys demeasne, as of fee, at the time of the sayed treason committed, or at any tyme after. And that after the deceasse of the same persone, so attaynted, all and singuler such persones and persone, as should haue had and enioyed such landes, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes, and other hereditamentes, as any persone, that at any tyme herafter shalbe attainted, of, or for, any treason aboue specified, shall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to be seazed, of anye estate in tayle, or for terme of lyfe, at the tyme of any suche Treason commytted, or at anye tyme after, shall after the death of the same persone, that so shall fortune to be atteinted, haue and
<pb facs="tcp:184040:10"/> enioye the saied landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes, in lyke maner and fourme, as though no suche Attayndour had been had, anye lawe or vsage, to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And ferthermore, it is ordeyned and enacted by the aucthoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue saied, that if anye persones, aboue the numbre of two, &amp; vnder the numbre of .xii. being assembled together, at any time after the saied .xii. daie of Februarie, shall intende, goe about, practice, or putte in vre, with force of armes, vnlawefullie, and of their awne auctoritie, to murder, kill, or slaie, any of the kinges Maiesties Subiectes, or to ouerthrowe, cut, breake, caste doune, or digge vp the Pales, Hedges, Diches, Wall, or other closure of any Parkes, Parke or other grounde enclosed, or the banke of any fishe Ponde or Poole, to the intente that thesame, or anye of them, from thensfurth, shoulde remaine open not enclosed, or voyde, or to haue Common, or waie in thesame Parkes or Parke, or other groundes or grounde enclosed, or in any of them, or to destroie any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Parkes, or Parke, or Fyshe ponde or Poole, or any Warreyns or Warreyn of Conies, or any Douehouses, or to pull, or cutte doune any house, Barne, Myll, or to burne any stackes of corne or graine, or alter, defalke, or abate the rentes or yerely value of any Manours, Landes, or tenementes, of any the kynges subiectes, or the price of any victuall, corne, or grayne, or any other thyng vsuall for the sustenaunce or appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of men, and beyng required, or commaunded by any Iustice of the Peace, or the shirife of the countie, or by any Mayor, Bailifes, or Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyfe, or other head officer, of any citie, or toune corporate, where suche assemblie shalbe had, by Proclamacion, to be made in the kynges name to retyre, or retourne to theyr habitacions, places, or houses, &amp; they so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by suche Proclamacion, shall not so dooe, but after that, shall in forcible maner, in fourme aforesaied, attempt to doe, or put in vre, anye of the thinges last aboue mēcioned: that then euery of thesame persones beyng aboue the numbre of two, and vnder the numbre of .xii. shall suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre imprisonmēt, of hys or their bodyes, by the space of one yere, without baile or mainprise, and shall make fine and raunsome, at the kinges will and pleasure. And also, that if any persone or persones, at anytime after the saied .xii. day of February, shalbe damnified or hurted, by the doing committing, or putting in vre, of any vnlawfull act or thyng aboue mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned: That then all and singular persones, so damnified or hurt, shall recouer &amp; haue damages with the costes of theyr suite, susteined in that behalfe, trebled agaynst the offendours therin.</p>
            <p>And for asmuche, as suche euyll dysposed persones, whiche of late tyme made Commocions and Rebellion, in certaine places, within this Realme, being but fewe in number, at such tyme, as they dyd begyn the same commocion, were not in short tyme, after the begynnyng therof, suppressed by strength, for that the kinges louing subiectes, for feare to incurre in daunger of the lawes of thys realme, durste not take vpon
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:184040:10"/> them so to doe, a great numbre of euill dysposed persones, dyd come and ioygne themselues to the saied small nūbre, wherby thesame euil dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed persones, tooke vpon them such boldnesse, that they would not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to obedience, without much bloudshedding, to the great daunger of the Kinges Maiesties persone, where, if the kinges louing subiectes durst haue taken vpon them, to haue suppressed them at the beginning, suche inconuenience and bloudshed shoulde not haue folowed: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is also ordeined and enacted, by the auctoritie aforesaied, that if any persones, aboue the numbre of twoo, that at any time, after thesaied xii. daie of Februarie, shalbe vnlawfullie, and of theyr awne aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, assembled together, to the entent with force of armes, to doe, practise, or put in vre, anye of the thinges aboue mencioned, that then it shalbe lawefull, to euery Iustice of Peace, and to euery Shirife, in any Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, being within the kinges Dominions, and to euery Maiour, Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life, and other head officer of any Citie, or Toune corporate, for the time he shalbe in Office, or any other persone or persones, hauing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Kinges Commission, or Letters from his highnes, or his priuie counsaill, aswel to rayse and assemble the kinges louyng Subiectes, in maner of warre to bee arayed, in suche great numbre, as he or they then shall thynke meete or able, to the intent by vyolence and strength to suppresse, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende, and take the sayed persones, that so shalbe vnlawfully assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. And that if the sayed persones, so vnlawfully assembled, after such commaundement or request by Proclamacion, or otherwise made, shall continue together, and not endeuour themselues, to retourne towardes theyr habitacions, houses or places, frō whence they come, in such short time, as they may conueniently: that then it shalbe lefull to euerye Ius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of peace, shirife, and also to euery Mayour, bailyfe, and other head Officer of any Citie, or Towne corporate, and to euery other persone, hauing aucthoritie, as is aforesaied, aftersuch commaundement, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest by Proclamacion made, and to suche persones, as shalbe assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, with any Iustice of peace, or shirife, or with any Mayour, bailife, or other head officer, of any Citie, or Toune corporate, and with euery other persone, hauing aucthoritie, as is afore sayed, to suppresse, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende, and take those persones, so vnlawfullye assembled, whiche after such request made, shall continue together, &amp; not endeuour themselues to retourne towardes theyr habitaciōs, or places frō whēce they came. And that if the saied persones, so vnlawfully assēbled together, or anye of them shall fortune to be killed, slaine, maimed, or hurt, in, or about the suppressing or taking of them: that then euery suche Iustice of Peace, shirife, Maiour, bailife, and other head officer, and euerye other persone hauyng aucthoritie as is aforesayed, and all and singular persones, by him or them assembled, shalbe free, dyscharged, and vnpunyshable, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well against the kyng, as against all and euery other persone and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones, of, for, or concernyng the kylling, slaying, maiming, and hurting,
<pb facs="tcp:184040:11"/> of any persone or persones, so vnlawfullye assembled, that shall fortune to be killed, slayne, maymed, or hurt, about, or by occasion of suppressing or taking of them.</p>
            <p>And ferthermor, be it enacted, by aucthoritie aforesaied, that all and euery Copieholder, or Customarieholder, being artificer, husbandman or labourer, and being of the age of xviii. yeres, or more, and vnder the age of .lx. yeres, not sicke, impotent, lame, maimed, ne hauing any other iuste, or reasonable excuse, or cause to the contrarie, and being required by the Shirife, Iustice or Iustices of Peace, or other hauing auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie by this Acte, or by Commission, or Letters, as is abouesaied, in that behalfe, (they declaring their saied aucthoritie,) or being required by the immediate lorde or lordes of whome such Copiholdes, or Custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marieholdes then shalbe holden, to serue the kinges Maiestie, for any the causes aboue rehearsed, &amp; refuse so to doe, shall onely during the life of suche persone or persones so refusing, forfeicte and lose, to his or their Lorde or Lordes, of whome such Copie or Customary holdes then shall be immediatlye holden, and shoulde be holden, duryng the lyfe of suche persone or persones so refusyng, in case he or they had not so refused, all theyr Copieholdes, and Customaryholdes. And that it shalbe lawfull to euery such Lorde or Lordes, theyr heyres or assignes, of whome such Copieholdes, or Customarieholdes shalbe immediately holden, and should haue been holden in case suche persone or persones had not so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused, by vertue of thys present acte, to entre and take into hys, or their handes and possession, all suche Copieholdes, and Customarieholdes so holden of them, or any of them immediatlye: and to reteyne the same duryng onely the lyfe of euery suche offendour or offendours, in suche maner and fourme, as he or they should haue had, the rentes or serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of suche Copieholde, or customary holde, in case such persone or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones so refusing had not refused. And that all and euery Fermour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng a yoman, husbandman, artificer, or labourer, and beyng of the age of .xviii. yeres or more, and vnder the age of .lx. yeres, not sicke, impotēt, lame, maymed, ne hauing any other iust or reasonable excuse, or cause to the contrary, &amp; being required by the shirife, Iustice, or Iustices of the peace, or other hauing aucthoritie by thys acte, or by commyssion or let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, as is afore saied, in this behalfe (they declaring their saied auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie) or being required by their Landelord, or landelordes, for the tyme beyng, to whome the rentes of suche Fermes shalbe then rysing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, or growing, to serue the kynges Maiestie, for any the causes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue rehearsed, and refuse so to doe, shall during onely the lyfe of suche Fermour or Fermours so refusing, forfeict and loose to such landelorde and landelordes, as should haue had the rentes of such Fermours, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the lyfe and liues of such persone or persones so refusyng, all their sayed Fermes. And that it shalbe lefull to euery such Landelorde and Landelordes, their heyres and assignes, to whome the Rentes of such
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:184040:11"/> Fermes shoulde haue been due, during the lyfe of such persone, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones so refusing, in case suche persone, or persones had not so refused, by vertue of this present acte, to enter and take into his or theyr handes or possession all suche Fermes, and to reteine the same, duryng onely the lyfe of euery such offendour or offendours. Prouyded alwaies, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that after the death of euery suche Copieholder, Customary holder, or fermour, as so shall offend, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feict any of theyr saied Copieholdes, Customary holdes, or fermes, as is afore saied, that then all &amp; euery such persone, and persones, as should or ought to haue had y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied copieholdes, customary holdes, or fermes, after, or by the death of such copieholder, customaryholder, or fermour, in case such copieholder, customary holder, or fermour, had not so offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ne forfeicted, shall and may haue the same copieholdes, customary holde, and Fermes, by entre, accion, admission, or otherwise, in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, fourme, and condition, and by suche wayes and meanes, as they &amp; euery of them should, might, or ought to haue had, if no such forfeicture or offence had been had, doen, or committed.</p>
            <p>And ferthermore it is ordeyned and enacted, by the aucthoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore saied, that if any persone or persones, after the sayed, xii. daye of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary, by open worde or deede, shall procure, moue, or styrre any other persone or persones to aryse, or make anye Trayterous or Rebellious assemblie, to thentent to doe, exercise, or put in vre anye of the thynges aboue mēcioned: that then euery persone so procuring, mouyng, or stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any other, shall therfore be demed, and adiudged a Felon, and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre peynes of death, and forfeicte his goodes, cattals, Landes, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes, as in cases of Felonie, and shall also leese the benefite of hys Clergie and Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>And also be it ferther enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that if any persone or persones, which at any time after the same daye, shalbe spoken vnto, moued, or styrred, to make any commocion, insurrection, or vnlawfull assemblie, for anye of the intentes aboue mencioned, and doe not within .xxiiii. houres next after he, or they shalbe so spokē vnto, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or styrred (onlesse he shall haue a good and reasonable cause of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse) declare the same to one Iustice of peace, or shirife of the sayed coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or to the Maior, Shirifes, Bailife, or Bailifes, or other head officer of any citie, or towne corporat, where such speaking, mocion, or styrring shalbe had, shall suffre imprisonmēt, vntill he shalbe dyscharged, by thre Iustices of peace, of the same shire, where the offence shalbe, wherof one of the saied Iustices shalbe of the <hi>Quorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is ordeined and enacted, by thaucthoritie abouesayed, that if anye persone or persones, beyng about the age of .xviii. yeres, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thage of .lx. yeres, beyng able to serue, and not sicke, lame, or impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, shalbe required by any Iustice of the peace, or anye shirife of anye Countie, where any such assemblie shalbe, or by any Maior, Bailife, or
<pb facs="tcp:184040:12"/> other head officer, of any Citie, borough, or Toune corporat, or by anye other, by the commaundement of any suche Iustice of peace, Shirife, Mayor, bailife, or other head officer, to goe with him or thē, to suppresse the persones vnlawfullye assembled, in maner and fourme afore sayed, that then euery persone so beyng able and required, doe willingly and obstinately refuse so to doe, shall suffre imprisonment of hys bodye, for one yere without baile or mainprise, and make fine and raūsome, at the kinges will and pleasure.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwaies, and it is enacted, by the aucthoritie aboue saied, that if the king, shall by his lettres patentes make any Lieutenaunt, in any countie or counties of thys Realme, for the suppressing of any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocion, Rebellion, or vnlawfull assembly: that then aswell all Iustices of peace, of euery such countie, and the shirifes, and shirife of the same, as all Mayours, bailifes, and other head officers, and all inhabitaūtes and subiectes, of anye Countie, Citie, Borough, or Towne corporate, within euery such countie, shall vpon the declaracion of the sayed let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres Patentes, and request made, be bounde to geue attendaunce, vpon the same Lieutenaunte, to suppresse anye Commocion, Rebellion, or vnlawfull assemblie, onlesse he or they, beyng so required, haue any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable excuse, for hys not attendaunce, vpon peyne of imprisonment for one whole yere.</p>
            <p>And be it ferther enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesayed, that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre and fourme of the Proclamacions, that shalbe made by the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of this acte, shalbe as herafter foloweth, or with the lyke ordre, and woordes in effect, that is to saye, the Iustice or other persone aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by this Acte, to make the saied Proclamacion, shall make or cause to be made an Oies, and after that, shall openly pronounce, or cause to be pronounced these woordes, or lyke in effecte. ¶ The Kyng our soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reygne Lord, chargeth, and cōmaundeth all persones beyng assembled immediatly to dysperse them selues, and peaceablie to depart to theyr habitacions, or to theyr lawfull busines, vpon the peynes conteyned in the act, lately made against vnlawfull, and rebellious assemblies. And GOD saue the king.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie afore saied, that if any persone or persones, doe, or shall molest, let, hynder, or hurte, any persone, or persones, that shall proclaime, or goe to proclayme, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Proclamacion and ordre made in the statute afore saied, wherby, such Proclamacion shall not be made: that then all and euery such persone and persones, so molesting, letting, hindering, or hurtyng, and all and euery suche persone and persones, offendour or offendours, to whome any suche Proclamacion or Proclamacions should, or ought to bee made, to the entente afore sayed, shall incurre, and bee in lyke daunger, &amp; suffre like peyne or peines, and forfeictures, as aforesaied, in euery of theyr degrees, as though the Proclamacion had been made
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:184040:12"/> any clause, article, or sentence, hertofore in thys acte included, made to the contrary, notwithstandyng. And be it enacted, by the aucthoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaied, that thys acte shalbe openly read, at euery quarter Sessions. <hi>SAVING</hi> to the Byshoppe of Duresme, and Byshoppe of Elie, and all other that haue chartre of the coūtie Palantine, and to their successours the yere, daye, and waste, in suche sort, as by the saied Chartre they had, or myght haue had the same, if thys Acte had neuer been had ne made: thys act, or any thing therin cōteined, to the cōtrary notwithstandyng. <hi>SAVING</hi> also, to all &amp; euery persone and persones, and heires in tayll, bodies politique and corporat, their heires, successours, and executours and to euery of them, other then to suche persone and persones onely, as shalbe attainted, cōuicted, or outlawed for any of the foresayed offences of Felonie or treason, &amp; their heires or the heyres of anye of them, clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng by dyscent in fee simple, from them, or any of them, all such right, tytle, entre, interest, leases, possession, rentes, condicions, profites, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and aduauntages, as they, or any of thē hath, or herafter shall haue, or of ryght ought to haue, in, or to any Honours, castles, manours landes, tenementes, woodes, rentes, reuersions, seruises, or heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, whatsoeuer, or in, or to, any part or parcel therof, to be forfeited, for any of the offences aforesaied, as if such attaindor or forfeycture, had neuer been had ne made, any thing in this Acte to the contrary, in anye wise notwithstanding. <hi>AND</hi> sauyng to all and euery bodye, &amp; bodies politique &amp; corporate, &amp; their successours, their liberties and fraūchises, in suche maner and fourme, as if this acte had neuer been had ne made. This acte to continue to the ende of the next Parlament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .vi. Chapitre. ¶ An Acte concerning the repeale of a braunche, of an Acte of Parlament, made in the last Session for buying of Tanned Lether.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here at youre Maiesties Parlament, holden at Westminster, vpon prorogacion, the .xiiii. daye of Marche, in thys present thyrde yere of your moste victorious reygne, emongest other thynges it was enacted, that no persone occupying the feate or mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, of Coriar, Cordewainer, sadler, Cobler, Gyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Letherseller, Bottelmaker, or anye other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer, shoulde from, and after the feast of Michaelmasse then next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, sell, or cause to be solde, or put to sale, anye Backes or Hydes, of any Englishe kynde of tanned Lether vnwrought, or in such kynde, as he shoulde buye the same, (Calues skynnes onely excepted) vpon peyne of forfeyting for euery Hyde, Backe, or parcell of lether, that he or they should so sell, contrary to the sayed Statute .x. shyllynges. Sithen the making of which act, great and innumerable inconueniences hath, and hereafter is lyke to come therof. Fyrst, neyther gyrdler, cordwainer,
<pb facs="tcp:184040:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:184040:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:184040:14"/> Sadler, Malemaker, bottelmaker, or any other artificer, vsing tanned lether in theyr art, is, or shalbe able, at anye time, at any instant, to serue the kinges Maiestie, his nobles, Lordes, &amp; commons, either of bootes, shooes, Gyrdles, Saddles, Barehydes, Males, Cofers, Pottes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges made of leather, for that the most parte of thartificers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresayed, been poore mē, not alwaies able to prouide store, of suche sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of leather, as should serue theyr tourne, in makyng such thinges, as is before mencioned, but must of necessitie, prouyde such leather, one of thē of another, as euer hertofore they haue accustomed to doe, whiche now by force of the extremitie of the sayed act, they may not doe, which is vnto the great hurt and hynderaunce, aswell of the kynges maiestie, as of his nobles, lordes, and commons, for that they, and euery of them be drieuē of necessitie to buye their lether, of a few persones, which been only mere regratours of the saied lether, at great, high, and vnreasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prices, to the great hurte of the common wealth, whereby the sayed artificers been not able, to aforde the saied wares made thereof, so good chepe, as they haue doen heretofore. And also, by reason of the foresayed restreynt or bondage, of the foresaied artificers, from buying and selling of lether: there is no mā sith that tyme, willing to set, or put hys or their chyldren to be prentise with anye of the foresayed artificers: for that not onely they, and euery of them, been brought in such bondage, by reason of the sayed acte, but also by the meanes wherof, are neuer lyke to grow to any necessary substaunce, neither by thexercise of theyr sayed handye craftes, to susteine the necessities of theyr olde age withal: and not onely that, but also in all cities, boroughes, corporate townes therby they lose benefite and commoditie, of theyr Chartre and Fredome. For reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion wherof, be it enacted, by thaucthoritie of this present Parlament, that it shalbe lawfull from hencefurth, to, and for euery of the sayed arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, or handie craftes men, expressed or named in the foresayed acte to buye and sell, all maner of tāned lether, corried, or not corried, so that such shalbe conuerted, by such buier, or buiers, vnto any kynd of wares or other thynges made of tanned leather, within thys realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, or other the kinges dominions, any wordes, penalties, or forfeic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, comprysed or specified, in the aboue remembred acte, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary herof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwaies, and be it enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that thys present acte, shall endure but onely vnto the ende of the nexte Parlament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .vii. Chapitre. ¶ An Acte for the repeale of a Statute, made in the xxv. yere of the reygne of King Henry theyght touching the takyng of Wildfoule, at certeyne times of the yere.</head>
            <pb n="xii" facs="tcp:184040:14"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the .xxv. yere of the reygne of your Maies<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties father, of most famous memorye, Kyng Henrye theyght, an acte was made, conteinyng two braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, wherof, the one was against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> taking of wyld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foule, betwene the last day of Maye, and the last day of August, with any nettes, or engins, vpon a peyne limited therupon, as in the sayed Statute, more largely doeth appeare: Forasmuche as the occasion of the sayed braunches, appeareth sithen to haue risen, but vpon a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate case, and that no maner of common commoditie is sithen perceiued to be growen of the same, being notably, by daily experience founde, and knowen that there is at thys present, lesse plentie of foule, brought vnto the markettes, then was before the making of the sayed Acte, whiche is taken to come of the punishement of GOD, whose benefite was ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by taken awaye from the poore people, that were wont to liue by theyr skill, in taking of the sayed foule, wherby, they were wont at that tyme to sustaine them selues, with their poore housholdes, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great sauyng of other kyndes of Victuall, of the whiche ayde they are nowe destitute, to their great and extreme impouerishyng: Humblye besechen your grace, your Maiesties true and faythfull subiectes, especiallye suche, as haue their places of habitacion, nigh vnto the Fennes, that all that braunche of the sayed Acte, made in the sayed .xxv. yere of your graces sayed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of most noble memorye touching the takyng of Wyldfoule, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is abouesayed, may be from hencefourth by your Maiestie, the Lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons in thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and vtterlye voyde, and of none effect, with all and euery article, sentence, matter, peynes, and forfeictures, conteyned, or otherwyse men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned in the sayed braunche, as if the same Acte had neuer been had, ne made.</p>
            <p>Prouyded, and be it enacted, by the aucthoritie abouesayed, that one other braunche, conteined in the sayed Acte, concernyng suche persones as shall presume by daye, or night willinglye to withdrawe, purloyne, take, distroye, or conueyghe, any maner of Egges, of any kinde of wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foule, from, or in any Nest, place or places, where they shall chaunce to be layed, by any kynde of Wildfoule, with euery article, sentence, matter, peynes, forfeictures, and prouisions, conteyned, or mencioned in thys sayed last braunche, shall stande in full strength, and effect, to all purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, intentes, and constructions, as if thys present acte had neuer been had nor made.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .viii. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte for the continuance of the Statute of Sewers.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:184040:15"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Herein the Parlament holden at Westmynster, by Prorogacion the .xv. daye of Ianuarye, in the .xxiii. yere of the most victorious reygne of our late So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne Lorde Kyng Henry theyght, emong other thynges, one generall Acte, concernyng Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Sewers, to be directed into all partes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realme, was enacted and made to continue and endure for twentie yeres, then next following, as by the same act more at large it doeth and maye appeare. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as the same Acte is thought good and beneficiall for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of this realme: Be it therfore enacted and ordeyned, by the king our Souereygne Lorde, with the assent of the Lordes Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall, and the commons in thys present Parlament as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that the sayed Acte, and all clauses, articles, and prouisions, in the same conteyned, shall continue &amp; endure in theyr force and strength, and to be obserued and kept for euer, in such maner and fourme, as shall and maye stande with the sequele &amp; addicions, herafter mencioned.</p>
            <p>And be it ferther enacted and established by the auctoritie aforesaied, that all skottes, lottes, and summes of money hereafter to be rated and taxed, by vertue of such commission of Sewers, vpon any of the landes tenementes, or hereditamentes, of our Soueraygne Lorde the kyng, hys heyres or successours, for any maner of thing or thinges, concerning the articles of the sayed commission of Sewers, shalbe gathered and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied, by distresse or otherwyse, in like maner and fourme, as shall or may be doen in the landes, tenementes, &amp; hereditamentes, of anye other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone or persones: and that all bylles of acquitaūce, signed with the hand or handes of such collectour or receiuour, as shall haue the collectiō ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the appoyntment of the sayed cōmyssioners, or .vi. of them, shalbe aswell a sufficient dyscharge, to the tenauntes, fermours, &amp; occupyers of the same groūdes, so to be charged for the sayed summe, wherwith theyr groundes shalbe so charged, as also a sufficiēt warrant to all and euery the receiuours, auditours, &amp; other whatsoeuer officer or officers, of our sayed souereygne lorde the kyng, his heyres, &amp; successours, for the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce to suche Tenaunt, Fermour, or Occupyer for the same, addyng moreouer vnto this acte, by aucthoritie of thys present parlament, that suche, and lyke fees, and none other, nor more, shalbe at any tyme payed or demaunded, for any Commission or Commyssions, or writtes of <hi>dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus potestatem,</hi> herafter to be sued out, or obteyned vnder the Seale of the Duchie, but onely such and lyke fees as been mencioned in the sayed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Acte, to be payed in the Chauncerie, for Commissions and writes of <hi>dedimus potestatem,</hi> to be obteyned from the same court of Chauncerie, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding moreouer therunto by thaunctoritie aboue saied, that euery cōmis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and cōmissions, herafter to be awarded for Sewers, shall continue
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:184040:15"/> and endure for terme of .v. yeres, next after the <hi>teste</hi> of suche commission oneles the same commission and commissions, shalbe otherwise dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, within the same by <hi>supersedeas,</hi> any thing or thinges mēcioned, or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in the saied former acte, contrarie to the addicions before menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, or any of them, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>The .ix. Chapiter. ¶ An acte for buiyng of rawe hides and Calues skinnes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche as lether is growen to an vnreasonable price, whereby the kinges Subiectes are not able at this daie to prouide them selfes, suche necessaries thereof made, as shoes, and botes, and suche like, at any reasonable price, as they heretofore haue doen, to the vtter empouerishement of diuers the Kynges louing and obedient subiectes: whiche said vnreaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable prices of lether doeth onely growe and rise, by reason of the vnsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable desire of diuers &amp; sundrie persones being no tāners, whiche day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in euery market, and other place buie &amp; regrate grene hides, in the heere and out of the heere to their handes, to the intent to sell the same to their awne lucre and gaine: Be it therefore enacted, by the king our Souereigne Lorde, the lordes spiritual and tēporal, and the commōs in this present Parlament assembled, and by thauctoritie of thesame, that no persone or persones within this realme, shal from, and after the feast of the Annunciation of our ladie next comming, buie, or cause to be bought any Calue skinnes or hides in the heere, or out of the heere, to the intent to sell againe the same vntanned, excepte onely suche persone and persones, as will tanne or tawe the same, vpon peine to forfeict for euery skinne or hide so bought, to thintent to sell againe, as aforesaied vi. s̄. viii. d. The one halfe of whiche forfeicture to be vnto our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Lorde the King: The other halfe to him or them that will sue for thesame, in any of the Kynges Courtes, by Byll, plaint, or other lawful processe, wherein no protection or wager of Lawe, nor yet any Essoine to the partie defendaunt shalbe allowed, or admitted.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>The .x. Chapiter. An acte for the abolishing and putting awaie of diuers bookes, and Images.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the Kīges most excellent Maiestie hath of late set fourth &amp; established by aucthoritie of Parlament, an vniforme, quiet, &amp; godlie ordre of common and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pē praier, in a boke ītitled <hi>The boke of common praier, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministraciō of the Sacramētes, and other rites and Ceremonies after the churche of England</hi> to be vsed &amp; obserued in the saied churche
<pb facs="tcp:184040:16"/> of Englāde, agreable to thordre of the primatiue churche, muche more comfortable vnto his louing subiectes, then other diuersitie of Seruice as heretofore of long time hath been vsed, being in the saied boke ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nothing to bee read, but the very pure worde of God, or whiche is euidentlie grounded vpon the same, &amp; in the other, thinges corrupte vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>true, vaine, &amp; supersticious, and as it were a preparatiō to supersticion, whiche for that they be not called in, but permitted to remaine vndefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, dooe not onely geue occasion to suche peruerse persones, as doo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the ordre and godly meaning of the kinges saied boke of cōmō praier, to cōtinue in their olde accustomed supersticious seruice, but also minister greate occasion to diuersitie of opinions, Rites, Ceremonies and Seruices: Bee it therefore enacted, by the kinge our Souuereine Lorde, the lordes Spiritual, and Temporall, &amp; the Commons in this present Parlament assembled, that all Bookes called Antiphoners, Missales, Grailes, Processionalles, Manuelles Legēdes, Pies, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuasses, Primers, in Latine or Englishe, Couchers, Iournalles, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalies, or other Bookes or writinges, whatsoeuer heretofore vsed for Seruice of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Churche, writen or Printed in the Englishe or Latine toungue, other then suche as are or shalbe set furth by the kinges Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, shalbe by auctoritie of this present acte, clearlie and vtterlie abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, extinguished, and forbidden for euer to bee vsed, or kepte in this Realme, or elswhere within any the kinges dominions.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that yf any persone or persones, of what estate, degre, or condicion soeuer he, she or they be, bodies politique or corporate, that now haue, or hereafter shall haue in his, her or their custodie, any the bookes or writings of the sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes aforesaied, or any Images of Stone, Timbre, Alebaster, or earthe, Grauen, Carued, or Painted, whiche heretofore haue been taken out of any Churche or Chappell, or yet stande in any Churche or Chappell, and dooe not, before the last daie of Iune next ensuyng, deface and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroie, or cause to be defaced and destroied, the same Images, and euery of them, and deliuer or cause to be delyuered, all and euery thesame boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to the Maiour, Baylife, Constable, or Churchewardens of the Toune, where suche Bookes then shal bee, to bee by theim deliuered ouer openlye within three Monethes nexte folowing, after thesaied deliuerie, to the Archebishoppe, Bishoppe, Chauncellour, or Comis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie of the same Dioceces, to the intent thesayed Archebishoppe, Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppe, Chauncellour, or Commissarie, and euery of them cause theim im̄ediatelie, either to be openlie brente, or other wayes defaced and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, shal for euerye suche Booke or Bookes willinglie reteined in his, her or their handes or custodie, within this Realme, or els where within any the kinges Dominions, and not deliuered, as is aforesaied, after the saied last daie of Iune, &amp; be thereof lawefullie conuicte, forfeict and loose to the king our Souereigne lorde, for the first offence, tenne
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:184040:16"/> shillinges. and for the seconde offence shal forfeict and lose being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of lawefullie conuict, foure poundes. And for the thirde offence, shal suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre imprisonment at the kinges will,</p>
            <p>And bee it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that yf anye maiors, Bailifes, constables, or churchewardens, dooe not within thre monethes after the receypte of thesame Bookes, delyuer or cause to bee deliuered, suche bookes so by them receiued, to the Archebishoppe, Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppe, Chauncellour, or Commissarie of theire dioces: And if the saied Archebishoppe, Bishoppes, Chauncellour, or Commissaries, dooe not with in fourtie daies after the receipt of suche bookes, burne, deface and destroie, or cause to be burned, defaced or destroied thesame bookes, &amp; euery of theme, that then thei and euery of them so offending, shall loose and forfeict to our Souereigne Lorde the king, being therefore lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie conuict, fourtie poundes: The one halfe of al suche forfeictures, shalbe to any of the kinges Subiectes, that will sue for thesame, in any of the kinges Courtes of Recorde, by Bill, plaint. Accion of debte or informacion, in whiche accion no Essoine, protection, wager of lawe or other delaie shalbe allowed.</p>
            <p>And for better execution of the same acte, beeit enacted by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie afore saied, that aswell Iustices of Assise in their circuites, as Iustices of peace, within the limites of their Commission in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral sessions, shal haue ful power and aucthoritie, to enquire of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aforesaied, and to heare and determine the same in suche fourme as theie may dooe in other suche like cases.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that this Acte or any thynge therin conteined, shal not extende to any Image or picture, set or granē vpon any tombe in any Churche, Chappel, or Churchyarde, onely for a monumēt of any King, Prince, Nobleman, or other dead persone, whiche hath not been commonlie reputed and taken for a saincte, but that all suche pictures, and Images maie stande and continue in like maner and fourme, as if this acte hade neuer ben had nor made, any thing in this act to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaie and be it enacted, by aucthoritie aforesaied, that any persone or persones maie vse, kepe, haue and retaine any Primers in the Englishe or latine toungue, set fourthe by the late Kinge of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memorie Kinge Henrie the eight, so that the sentences of inuoca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion or praier to Sainctes, in the same Primers, be blotted or clearlie put out of the same, any thing in this Acte to the contrarie notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xi. Chapiter. An Acte that the kinges Maiestie maie nominate and. appoincte .xxxii, persones, to peruse and make Ecclesiasticall lawes.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:184040:17"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L bee it the kynges moste excellent Maiestie gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ruler vnder GOd of this Realme, ought moste iustlie to haue the gouernement of his subietes and the determinacion of their causes, aswell ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall as temporall, yet the same, as cōcerning Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall causes hauing not of long time been put in vre nor exercysed, by the reason of the vsurped au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thortie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Bishoppe of Rome, be not perfeictlie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande nor knowen of his subiectes, and therfore of necessitie, aswel for the abolishing and putting to vtter obliuion the saiede vsurped auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, as for the necessarie administracion of iustice, to his louing sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes: It maie please his highnesse, that it maie be enacted by his most gracious assent with the assent of the Lordes Spirituall and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and the Commons of this present Parlamente assembled, and by thaucthoritie of the same, that the kinhes Maiestie shal from hensforth during thre yeares, haue full power, aucthoritie, and libertie, to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and assigne by the aduise of his highnesse counsail sixtene persons of the clergye, wherof foure to be bishoppes, and sixtine persones of the Temporalitie, wherof foure to be learned in the common lawes of thys Realme, to peruse and examine the Ecclesiasticall lawes of longe time here vsed. And to gather, ordre, and compile suche lawes Ecclesiastical as shalbe thought to his Maiestie, his saied Counsail, and them or the more parte of them, conuenient to be vsed, practised and set furth with in this his Realme, and other his dominions, in all Spirituall or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall Courtes and conuencions. And if after suche nominacion any of the persones so to be nominated happē to die, that then his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse by the aduise of his said Counsaill, during the saied three yeres, shall haue full power and aucthoritie, from time to time to nominate and assigne other in their places to supplie thesaied numbre of two and thirtie persones. And that thesaied twoo and thirtie persones so nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as is aforesaied. at all times from time to time, during the sayede three yeres, shal hauefull power and aucthoritie to assemble them selfes by his highnesse commaundement, for the perfeict colleccion, compiling and ordering of thesaied lawes. And be it also enacted by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforesaied, that suche lawes Ecclesiasticall so compiled, gathered and ordered by thesaied twoo and thirtie persones, or the more numbre of them, and sette furth, published, and declared by the Kinges Maiesties Proclemacion, with thesaied aduise vnder his highnesse great Seale shal by vertue of this present acte be onely taken, reputed, practised, and put in vre for the kinges Ecclesiastecall lawes of this Realme and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, any lawe Statute, vsage or prescripcion, to the contrarye thereof notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and it is ordeyned and enacted by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforesayed, that no maner of persone or persones shall at anye time
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:184040:17"/> hereafter incurre, or bee in any contempt, peine, forfeicture or losse, or in daunger of any accion, or suite of premunire, by meane or occasiō of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting, or putting in exercise of any Lawes or matter, whiche shalbe deuised by the saied twoo and thirtie, or the more parte of them, and set furth by Proclamacion vnder the great Seale of Englande, or for hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any maner of Plee, or making of any Processe, touching or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any suche Lawes or matter, any Estatute, lawe or Custome to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also and be it enacted by the aucthoritie abouesaied, that all and euery Ecclesiasticall Iudge and ministre, that shal execute any thing by vertue of any suche lawes so to be set furth, as is abouesaied, shall from time to time obeie the kinges write and writes of prohibici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of attachement, vppon prohibicion and Indicauit, and not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede contrarye to the tenour of suche write or writes, in suche and the same manour, fourme, and condiciō as thei haue, or ought to haue doen before the making of this acte, any thing in this acte to the contrarie in any wise notwitstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies and be it enacted, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aucthoritie afore sayed, that this acte or any thing therin conteined shall not extende, or be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretated, to geue any aucthoritie to the sayd twoo and thirtie perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or to the more numbre of them, or to the Kinges highnesse, for to compile, stablishe, publishe or set furth any Ecclesiasticall lawe repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt, or contrarie to any commō lawe or Statute of this realme, any thing in this acte to the contrarie not withstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte for the ordering of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall Ministers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche as concorde and vnitie to bee had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Kinges Maiesties Dominions, it is requisite to haue one vniforme fashion and maner, for making and consecrating of Bishoppes, Priestes, Deacons, or Ministers of the Churche: Bee it therefore enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Kynges highnesse, with the assent of the Lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this present Parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that suche forme and maner of making, &amp; consecrating of Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishoppes, Bishoppes, Priestes, Deacons, and other Ministers of the churche, as by sixe Prelates, and sixe other men of this Realme learned in goddes lawe, by the kinges Maiestie to be appoincted and assigned or by the moste numbre of them shalbe deuised for that purpose, and set furth vnder the greate Seale of Englande, before the first daie of April nexte comming, shal by vertue of this present Acte, bee lawefullie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised and vsed, and none other: any Estatute, Lawe or vsage to the
<pb facs="tcp:184040:18"/> contrarie, in any wyse notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xiii. Chapiter. An acte for the restitucion in bloude, of Sir William Sharing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here sir William Sharington knight, aswell by the Course of the Common Lawe of this Realme of Englande, as by acte of Parlament, was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie attainted of high Treason, and other offences, by reason whereof he is depriued, and dishabled in bloude and name to demaunde, aske, haue, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioie suche Manours, Landes, Tenementes, and Hereditamentes, as shoulde or might come, des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende, remaine, or reuert to him from any his lineall or collaterall aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestour or auncestours, to whom he should or might be heire in bloude. And where our Souereigne Lorde the Kinge, that nowe is, of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundaunt clemencie, pitie, charite, especiall grace and mere mocion and by thaduise of his honorable counsaile, by his graces letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes vnder his greate Seale of Englande, bearing date at Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster the fifth daie of Nouembre, in the thirde yere of his reigne: hathe perdoned, remitted and released, vnto the saied sir William Sharyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton by the name of William Sharington late of London knight, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise called William Sharinton of London knight, otherwise called William Sharinton knight, otherwise called William Sharinton of Laicoke in the countie of Wilteshire knight, or by what other name, or surname, or addicion of name, or surname, he were knowen or called, all highe treasons and offences committed and doen by him, before the saied fifth daie of Nouembre as by thesame letters Patentes of perdon more plainelie appeareth. Our saied Souereigne Lorde the king at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> humble peticiō and sute of thesaied Sir William Sharington, is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and contented, that it bee enacted, and established by his highnesse, with the assent of the Lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this present Parlament assembled, and by thaucthoritie of thesame: that thesaied Sir William Sharington shalbe clearlie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, acquited, released, and discharged of al and singular Treasons, and other offences mencioned, or expressed in the saied attaindour, or Attaindours, or Acte of Parlamente, or any of them, or whereof thesame Sir William was attainted, or conuicted before thesaied fifth daie of Nouembre, in thesaied thirde yeare of the reigne of our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Lorde the king that now is, and of all Iudgements, emprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, peines of death, and other peines, and penalties, whiche by reason thereof Sir William Sharington shoulde or myght in any
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:184040:18"/> wise incurre, haue, suffre, or susteine. And that thesame Sir William Sharington, and his heires frō hensfurth maie and shal by auctoritie of this present Acte, bee restored and enhabled in bloude, and name to sue and be sued, impleade, and bee impleded, and to demaunde, aske, haue, and enioie all and singuler suche Manours, Landes, Tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and hereditamentes, wyth theyr appurtenaunces whatsoeuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, which at any time hereafter shall descende, come, or reuerte from any lineall or collaterall Auncestour, or Auncestours of the saied Sir william Sharington, as heire or heires to thesame Auncestour, or aūcestours, in suche maner, and fourme, as if thesaied Sir william Sharington had neuer been attainted. And that thesaied sir william Sharington, and al and singular the children and issues of the bodie of thesaied sir william Sharington, and all and euery other persone, and persones being of thole bloude to thesaied sir William Sharington, maie, and by aucthoritie of this present Acte shalbe from hensfurth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored, and enhabled in bloude and name, to demaunde, aske haue, and enioie, all and singuler suche Manours, Landes, Tenemētes, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditamentes, with their appurtenaunces whatsoeuer thei bee, whiche at any time hereafter shall descēde, Reuert, Remayne, come or growe to thesaied sir William Sharington, or his heires by discēt, Purchase, Gift, or otherwise, in suche, thesame, and like maner, fourme, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion to al ententes, constructions, and purposes, as if thesaied sir William Sharington hadde neuer been attainted. And that thesame sir William Sharington his Executours and administratours shall and maie in his or their awne name and names, sue, Aske, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, all suche Debtes, Couenauntes, and other thinges, to the saied sir william Sharington Growen, dewe hadde, or made, by, or vpon any writing, specialtie, or recorde, at any time before thesaied Attaindour or attaindours, which the Kinges Highnesse hath or shall by his Letters Patentes, or otherwise geue, Graunt, Appoint, or Assigne, to thesaied sir William Sharington, and the Moneie and other profeicte thereof comming, to Conuerte, haue, and retaine to the vse of the saied Sir William Sharington, his executours, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministratours, in suche thesame, and in like maner, fourme, and condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to all intentes, construccions, and purposes, as if thesaied Sir William Sharingtō shoulde or might haue doen, if he had neuer been attainted.</p>
            <p>And be it ferther enacted by the auctoritie abouesaied, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied sir William Sharington shal haue &amp; enioie al suche fredomes, liberties, fraunchises, and priuileges within the Citie of Lōdon, and elswhere, aswell within the realme of England, as without, as he had, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioied before thesaied attaindour or attaindours, in suche sorte, fourme and condicion as he hadde and enioied, or of right ought or might haue hadde, or enioied thesame, if thesaied Attaindour or Attaindours,
<pb facs="tcp:184040:19"/> or any of them had not been had nor made, any forfeicture, iugement, Lawe, Statute, vsage, Custome, priuilege, or other thinges to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie not withstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xiiii. Chapiter. ¶ An act for the restitucion in bloude of Marie Seimour, daughter to Sir Thomas Seimour knight, Lorde Seimour of Sudleie, late Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of Englande.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N most humble wise sheweth vnto your highnesse, your faithful subiect Marie Seimour daughter of sir Thomas Seimour knight, late lorde Seimour of Sudleie, &amp; late highe Admirall of Englande, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gottē of the bodie of quene Katherine late quene of Englande and late wife to the saied Thomas lorde Seimour, and before that, wife to your moste noble father of most famous memorie king Hērie theight That where as thesaied Thomas lord Seimour by auctoritie of your highnesse court of Parlamēt, holden at westminster, in the seconde yere of your most noble reigne, was iustelie attainted of high treason, &amp; by reasō thereof your saied subiecte standeth, and is a persone in her bloud and Image corrupted: It maie please your highnesse of your most noble &amp; aboundaunt grace, that it maie be at the hūble peticion of your saied subiecte ordeined, established and enacted by your highnesse, with thas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser of the lordes spirituall and temporal, and of the cōmons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parlamente assembled, and by aucthoritie of thesame, that your saied subiecte, and her heires maie bee and shalbe, by aucthoritie of this act, restored and enhabled onely in bloude, as daughter &amp; heire &amp; heires to thesaied Thomas lorde Seimour. And that your saied subiecte and her heires from hensfurth maie and shalbe enhabled to demaunde, aske, haue, holde, and enioie, al &amp; euery suche honors, castels, manours, lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippes, hūdredes, franchises, liberties, priuileges, aduousōs nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, presentacions, knightes fees, landes, tenemētes, rentes, reuersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, seruices, remainders, porcions, annuities, pencions, rightes, &amp; all maner of hereditamēts, with their appurtenances, which at any tyme here after shal come, remaine, discēde or reuert from any collateral aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestour of your saied subiect, other then suche castels, manours, landes, tenementes, rentes, reuersions, seruices, remainders, porcions, annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, pencions, rightes, and al maner of hereditaments with theire appurtenances, whiche were of the saied Thomas lorde Seimour her father in possession, reuercion, remainder, or otherwise, the daie of the attaindor of the saied Thomas lorde Seimour, or at any time after the treason by him cōmitted or doen: And other then suche honours, castels, manours, lādes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes as your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse was, or is intitled to haue, or might, or ought to haue vpon any
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:184040:19"/> Office found or to be founde, by force of the said Attaindour in suche the same and like maner, fourme, and condicion, to al intētes, construc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and purposes, as if the saied Thomas Lorde Seimour father to your saied subiect had neuer been attainted, and as though no suche at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taindour of the saied Thomas Lorde Semour had euer been hadde or made. And that your saied Subiecte and her heires maie hereafter vse and haue any Action or suite, and make her pedegree and conueiaunce in bloude as heire, aswell to and from her saied father, as also to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther persone, or persones, in like maner, fourme, and degree to all inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, construccions, and purposes, as if the saide Thomas lord Seimour hadde neuer been attainted, and as if no suche attaindour were or had been had, the corrupcion of bloude betwene the saied Thomas Lorde Seimour, and your subiecte, and her heires, or any acte of parlament, or Iudgement concerning the attindour of the saide Thomas Lorde Seimour, or any other thing, whereby the bloude of the saied Thomas Lorde Seimour is, or shoulde be corrupted, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> contrarie in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies and bee it enacted, by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that this present acte, or any thing therein conteined, extend not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store or entitle your saied Subiecte, or any of her heires to any suche Honours, Castels, Lordshippes, Manours, Landes, Tenements, or other Hereditamentes, whiche your highnesse now hath or hadde, or is, might, or ought to bee intiteled to haue, by reason of any Attaindour or Attaindours, of thesaied Thomas Lorde Seimour, nor shall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to any Honours, Castels, Lordshppes, Manours, Landes, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes, Rentes, Reuersions, Seruices, or other Hereditamentes, late of the saide Thomas Lorde Seimour, whiche your highnesse hath heretofore geuen, dimised, exchaunged or graunted to any persone or persones, in Fee simple, Fee taile, or for, terme of life, lyues, or yeres, or at will, But that all suche Honours, Castels, Lordeshippes, Manours Landes, Tenementes, Reuersions, Seruices, and Hereditamentes whiche your Hignesse hathe geuen, dimised, exchaunged, or graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as is aforesaied, Shall stande, Remaine, abide, And continue in thesame estate, force, degree, and condicion, to all intentes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struccions and purposes, as thei and euery of theim were before the making of this Acte, and as though this Acte hadde neuer been hadde nor made. Sauing to all and euery other persone and persones, bodies politique or corporate, their heires and successours, and to the heires and successours of euery of them, all such estate, possession, ryght, title interest, reuersion, remainder, lease and leases, claime, condicion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and all other profeictes and commodities, as thei haue or ought to haue, out, in, or to the premisses, or any parte or parcell thereof, as though this act had neuer ben had ne made. And your saied subiect shal dailie praie to God for your most noble grace in honor long to cotinue</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:184040:20"/>
            <head>¶ The .xv. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte against fonde and Phantasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prophecies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here now of late Sithens the prorogacion of the last session of this present Parlament, diuers euill disposed persones, mynding to stirre and moue se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion, disobedience &amp; rebellion, haue of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse mindes, feined, Imagined, inuented, publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed and practised diuers Phantasticall &amp; fonde Prophecies, concerning the kinges Maiestie &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers honorable persons, Gentlemen, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of this Realme, to the great disturbaunce and peril of the kinges Maiestie, &amp; this his realme: For remedie therof, be it ordeined &amp; enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the king our Souuereine lorde, with thassēt of the lordes Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual &amp; Temporal, and of the cōmons in this present Parlament assē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, &amp; by the auctoritie of thesame, that if any persone or persons, after the fist daie of Februarie next cōming, do set furth in writing, printing, singing, speaking, and publishe or otherwise declare, to any persone or persones, any phantastical or false Prophecie, vpon occasion of any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, fieldes, beastes, foules, badges, and such other like thinges, accus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed in armes, coginsaunces, or Signetes. or by reason of any time, yere, or daie, name bloudshed or warre, to the intēt thereby to make any rebellion, insurrection, dissencion, losse of life or other disturbaūce, with in the Realme, or other the kinges dominions: That then euery suche persone thereof being lawfullie indicted, &amp; conuicted, according to the due course of the lawes, for euery suche offence shall suffer imprisonmēt of his bodie, by the space of one yere, without Baile or Mainprise, and shall forfeict for euery suche offence the summe of ten poundes.</p>
            <p>And if any suche offendour doe after suche cōuiction eftsones offende in any of the premisses, and be therof lawfullie indicted, and conuicted by the due course of the lawes, that then euery suche offendour shall for his secode offence &amp; conuiccion, as is aboue saied, suffre imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his body, without baile or mainprise, during his life, and shall forfeict all his goodes, and cattalles, reals, and personales, the moities of eueri whiche forfeictures shalbe to the Kinge, and the other moities thereof to him, that shall or will sue for thesame in any of the Kinges Courtes of recorde, by accion. bil, plaint or informacion, in whiche case no essoine, wager of lawe, or proteccio shalbe allowed or admitted.</p>
            <p>And be it farther enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that all and euery Iustice of Assise. Iustice of Oier &amp; determiner, Iustice of peace shal haue ful puwer and aucthoritie by vertue hereof, to enquire, heare, and determine al and euery offence, or offences abouesaied, commited, or doen within the limites of their commission, contrarie to the tenour and meaning of this acte.</p>
            <pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:184040:20"/>
            <p>Prouided alwaies and be it enacted, by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that no persone nor persones, shall at any time hereafter be empeched, for any offence hereafter to bee committed or doen, contrarie to this acte onlesse he be therefore empeched, or accused, within sixe Monethes next ensuing any such offence, by him or them committed to bee doen. And this act to endure to the end of the nexte Parlament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xvi. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte touching the punishement of Vacabondes and other idle persons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche as it is notoriouslie sene &amp; knowen, that Vacabondes &amp; beggars doe dailie encrease Within this y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Kinges highnesse realme into very great nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, chieflie by occasion of idelnesse, mother and rote of al vices, whereby doe ensue cōtinual theftes, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, conspiracies and other soundrie heinous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; partelie for that the good and holsome lawes and Statutes of this realme, hath not been put in due execution, and partelie also, by reasō of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> multitude of thesame (thextremitie of some whereof haue been occasiō that they haue not been put in vre). Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore &amp; for diuerse good cōsideracions it is enacted by the king our Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereine Lorde, with the assent of the lordes Spirituall &amp; Temporal, and the commons in this present Parlament assembled, &amp; by thaucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the same, that the Statute made in the first yere of the kinges highnesse moste noble reigne concernīg idle persones and vacabondes in certaine cases, to be made slaues and so furth, and all and euery arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, matier, prouiso, braunche and sentence therein conteined shalbe frō hensfurth vtterlie repealed, made frustrate, voide, and of none effecte.</p>
            <p>And that the Statute, concerning how aged &amp; impotent persones shoulde be ordred for their better Reliefe, &amp; how Vacabondes &amp; strōg beggars shoulde bee punished, made in the .xxii. yere of the late kinge of moste famous memorye kyng Henrie the eight, and euery matyer, article, prouiso, braūche, &amp; sentence therein conteined, to be from hens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furth reuiued, made good, and stand in full strengthe and vertue and shal continue and remaine a perfeicte Act of parlament for euer.</p>
            <p>And be it therfore enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaid, that all Ius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices of peace, and euery of them within the limites of their commission and the Maiours, Shirifes, Bailifes, and other officers within their seueral Rules and offices, shal within their seuerall limites assemble together, and make their seuerall diuision, according to the purport and effecte of this acte, at the next general quarter Sessions of the peace to be holden after the feast of Easter nexte to come, for the due, spedie, and diligent execution of the same Acte. And that if any suche aged or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent
<pb facs="tcp:184040:21"/> person after the feast of easter nexte to come, shall offende con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to this Estatute, that then thesaied offendour shalbe vsed and punished, as in the same Estatute of the .xxii. of king Henrie theight, is prouided. And that before the feast of Easter no punishment shalbe put in execucion against any suche Impotent, Lame, and aged persone, but onely by the discrecion of the nexte Iustice of peace of the same Shire where suche offendour shalbe apprehended, any thinge in the saied acte to the contrarie notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And for the auoiding of the Idle loitering of common labourers of husbandrie, within this Realme: Be it enacted by the aucthoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied, that suche common labourers being persones able in bodie, vsing loitering, and refusing to woorke, for suche reasonable wages, as is moste comonly geuen in the parties, where suche persones shall dwell shalbe for euerie suche times, as he or they refuse to laboure, hauīg rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable wages, as is aforesaied, adiudged Vacabondes, and shalbe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished as strong, and mightie vacabondes, in suche maner and fourme as is declared in the saide act of .xxii. against vacabōdes. And touching maimed, lamed, and sore, aged, and impotent persons, whiche resorteth to the Citie of London, and to other Cities, Tounes, and Villages on begging: Be it enacted by the auctoritie aforesaied that all and singuler Maiours, Shirifes, Bailifes, Constables, or other heade Officers of any Citie, Toune, or Village, to whiche suche resorte is, or shalbe, shall before the feast of the Purification of oure Lady next folowing, see all suche Idle, impotent, maimed, and aged persones, who otherwist can not by their discrecions bee taken for vacabondes, whiche were borne within the saied Citie, Toune, or Village, or hath been there moste cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersant and abiding by the space of three yeres, and now decaied, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed &amp; prouided for, of the tenauntries, Cotages, or other conuenient houses, to be lodged in, at the Costes and Charges of the saied Cities; Tounes Boroughes, and Villages, there to be relieued, and cured by the deuocion of good people of the saied Citie, Boroughe, Toune, or Village, and that they doe not suffer after the time before rehersed, any other then suche as either were borne, or hath been for the moste parte conuersant, or abiding by the space of three yeres, as is aforesaied, in the saied Citie, Boroughe, Toune, or Village, to remaine &amp; begge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade within the precinctes of suche Cities, Tounes, Villages, or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes. Except it be suche as haue letters, or are aucthorised or licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by force of this act, vpō peine that euery suche Maiours, Shirifes and bailifes, Constable, or other head officer by what name soeuer he be called, suffering any persone to begge within the precinct of his or their suche Iurisdiccion, other then is before rehearsed, for euery three daies, shall forfeict tenne shillinges, to whomsoeuer will sue therefore, by Bill, Informacion, or accion of debte, in any Courte of recorde, in the whiche sutes no Essoine, ne wager of Lawe, or proteccion shall bee
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:184040:21"/> allowed for the defendaunt.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iour of the citie of London, and al other Maiours, Bailifes, Shirifes, Constables, and other head officers of euery Citie, Borough, or Toune corporat, and of euery other Toune and village, dooe with al conuenyēt spede by themselfes, or their sufficient deputies, before the feast of the Purification of our Ladie nexte comming, and so from tyme to tyme euery Moneth once, make a viewe and examinacion of aged, impotent and lame persones, beggers, as bee within the precincte of their Iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and see all suche as were not borne, nor hath been for the moste parte conuersaunt and abiding by the space of three yeres complete, or haue not letters, and aucthorised or licenced by force of this Estatute, conueighed on horseback, Carte, or otherwise, as shal seme by their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecions, to the next Constables, and they to conueie thesame to the next Constables, and so from Constables to Cōstables, till thesaied persones be brought to the place where thei were borne, or most conuersaunt and abiding, as is aforesaied, there to be prouided for, kepte, and nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed of almes as is aforesaied, vpō the peine that euery suche Maiour, Shirif, or Constable, headborough, or other head officers not making viewe, nor sending or conueiyng away, nor receiuing or not prouiding, as is before appointed, according to the true purporte, or meaning of this acte, to forfeicte for euery suche default ten shillinges, whereof the one halfe to be to the kinges vse, and thother to the partie, that wil sue therefore in any of the kinges Courtes of Recorde, by bil, informacion, accion of debt, in the which suites no essoine, wager of law, or protecciō shalbe allowed for the defendaunt.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and bee it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayed that if any of thesayed aged, maimed, or impotent persones of the cities Tounes, or villages, where they were borne in, or had their moste abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as is aforesayed, bee not so lame, or impotent, but that thei maie worke in some maner of worke: that then suche Citie, toune, parishe, or village dooe either in common prouide some suche worke for them, as they maie be occupied in, or appoincte them to suche as will finde them worke for meate and drinke. And if they refuse of wilfulnesse and stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernesse to worke, or dooe runne awaie &amp; begge in other places, then to punishe the same according to their discrecions, with stocking, beating, or otherwise, as shall seme to them conuenient.</p>
            <p>Be it also enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that all Leprouse and poore beddred creatures, whatsoeuer thei bee, maie at their awn liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie remaine and continue in suche houses appointed for leprouse or bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred people, as they now bee in, and shall not bee compelled to repaire into any other Countryes or places by vertue of this Acte, any thing therein contemed to the contrarie notwithstanding. And that also it shalbe lawefull vnto the saide Leprouse, and beddred people, for their
<pb facs="tcp:184040:22"/> better Reliefe to appointe their proctour, or proctours, so there bee not appoincted aboue the numbre of twoo persones, for any one house of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouse, or beddred people, to gather the charitable almes of all suche in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes, as shalbe within the compasse of foure miles of any of the saied houses of Leprouse and beddred persones.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies and be it enacted by thaucthoritie afore saied, that it shalbe lawefull to the lord Chauncellour of Englande, or lorde keper of the greate Seale for the time beinge, at their discrecions, to graunt commission vnder the greate Seale of Englande, to euery or any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone or persones, that hath, or shall haue his or their houses, or barnes burnt, or suche losses, or to suche as bee or shalbe Leprous persones, to gather the reliefe and charitie of others for their reliefe, or for their aide and helpe of his or their losses, decaie or hinderaūce, as in time past hath been vsed, any thing in this acte notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that all and euery Statute and acte of Parlament made for punishmente of Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bondes, Slaues, aged and impotēt persones, or any of them, and euery article, sentence, clause, or prouiso therin conteined, other thē this presēt act and Statute made, &amp; the saied act made in the saied .xxii. yere shall be from hensfourth vtterlie voide, repealed, and of none effecte or force.</p>
            <p>And forasmuch as diuerse women and men going on begging, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and lame, &amp; some able enoughe to laboure, doe carie children abouts with them of tendre age, and some of foure .v.vi. yeres of age or yonger or elder, whiche being once brought vp in idlenesse, will hardelie bee brought after to any good kinde of labour, peine, trauail, or seruice.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by thauctoritie aforesayed, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> if anye childe aboue thage of .v. yeres, and vnder thage of .xiiii. goe about wandering, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied, or els alone, in case anye maner persone that is able to kepe anye suche childe will take it, be it male or female, of and from any suche beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger beinge the father or mother thereof, nouricer or keper, whether they be willing or not, or without any suche nourice, father, mother or keper, by him or her selfe wādering, and bring such childe so taken, before one of the Cōstables of the parishe, where the childe shall so fortune to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp, &amp; at the next general quarter sessions to be holden in that Shire nexte to the place wher the saied taking vp shall fortune to bee, present the same in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> presence of the saied Constable, before the Iustice of peace at the same Sessions, and there in open Sessions promise to bring the same childe vp in some honest labour or occupacion, till the womā child come to thage of .xv. yeres, &amp; the mā childe to thage of .xviii. yeres, if the Master or mastresse shal chaunce so long to lyue, that then and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied Iustices of peace by their discreciō shall adiudge by vertue of this acte, the saied childe, vnto the ages before specified, to be seruaūt or seruauntes to the saied persone or persones so taking and promising as is afore saied, suche childe to bee vsed and ordred, in all poinctes
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:184040:22"/> according as the lawe, &amp; custome of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> realme is of seruauntes without wages, to what labour, occupacion, or seruice soeuer thesaied taker vp, or Maister or mastres shal appoint him, or her, during thesaied terme, and the saied iudgement shalbe entred by the Clerke of the peace in the saied Sessions in fourme folowing. <hi>Memorandum, that at the Sessions of the peace holden at. w. the daie. &amp;c. one I. B. of the toune of L. had deliuered to him, according to the forme of the Statute in that case prouided B.T. estemed to be of thage of seuen, or eight yeres, to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred according to the forme of the saied Statute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if it shall fortune suche child so adiudged to runne awaie at any time, ones, or mo times from his, or her maister, or maistres, that then it shalbe lawful for euery suche Maister, or Maistres, to take the sayed childe againe, and to kepe, and punishe the saied childe in the stockes, or otherwise by discrecion, or otherwise at the libertie of suche Maister, or maistres, to haue a warraunt from any Iustice af peace in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same shire where the childe so runnes awaie, for suche childe running awaie, or going awaie, as is prouided by the statute of labourers, for suche Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts as depart awaie from their Maister, or Maistres, without a reasonable cause before thende of their terme.</p>
            <p>And that euery Iustice of Peace, shall by force of this acte haue auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and power, to make suche warraunt against euery suche persō so going, and running awaie, in like forme as they, or any of them maie dooe against any seruaunt departing out of his maisters seruice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out licence, or reasonable cause, and by force of the same warraunte the childe so running, or going awaie to be taken, and ordred in euery de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as is prouided by the saied statute labourers for seruantes depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of their maister, or mastres seruice, as is afore saied.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie afore saied, that if, and as often as it shal chaunce the father, mother, norice, or other bearer abou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the childe, or any other persone, or persones, to steale, or entice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie any such child, adiudged for a seruaunt, as is afore saied, that thē, &amp; so often it shalbe lawfull for the maister, or maistres of the same childe to be at his, or their libertie to take an accion vpon the statute Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers against euery suche persō so stealing, or entising awaie suche child as he, or they might haue, by reasō of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied statute labourers, against him, or them that retaines any mannes seruant out of his Seruice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thende of the saied terme, or els to take an accion of trespas against suche offendor, in whiche accion he shal recouer his dammages, &amp; treble costes of his sute.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie afore saied, that if y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> master, or mastres to whome such child, as is afore saied shalbe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged to bee Seruaunt, be vnreasonable in ordring, and bringing vp of suche childe, that then at all times vpon complainte made at the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral quarter sessiōs of peace, in the countie where the saied child shalbe
<pb facs="tcp:184040:23"/> by two honest neighbors of the same place, or toune wher y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied childe shall fortune to be so vnresonably ordred, if it shall appere by honest wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to the iustices of peace at the same sessiōs, the cōplaint therof made shalbe true, then the iustices of peace at their general sessiōs in the same shire, where suche cōplaint shalbe made, shall by vertue of this act haue aucthoritie, and power to discharge y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied childe from his, or their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable maister, or maistres, and appoint the same to some other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest maister, or maistres, vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied ages, to be ordred in euery degre, as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied childe shoulde haue been with his former maister or maistres &amp; that ordre, and appoinctment to be written in the booke of the Clerke of the Peace, for the whiche entrie the saied clerke of the Peace shal haue iiii. d. for his labour, &amp; not aboue, and in like maner shall haue .iiii. d. and not aboue, for the fyrst entrie of the chylde, to be seruant, as is aforesaid, to be paied be the maister, or maistres of the saied childe.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted, by thauctoritie aforesaid, that if the woman childe to be appointed a seruaunt, as is aforesayd, be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried before her age of .xv, yeres, that thē by that mariage, she shalbe dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of seruice. This Acte, or any thing therin conteined to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesayed, that all, and euery Vacabonde, or begger being borne in any other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciō, or coūtrie thē within this realme, shall in maner, &amp; forme aforesayd and vppon the forfeictures, &amp; penalties before mencioned, be cōueighed from place to place, or to the place, or Marches next adioining, to hys, or their natiue coūtrie, or to the next port, if there be a sea betwene thys realme, and his, or their saied countries, there to bee kept of thinhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes of the said next porte, in conuenient labour from idlenesse, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise til they maie be cōueighed ouer, and then at the costes of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes of the saied porte, if theimselues shall not haue wherewith, to be conueighed ouer into their natiue countries.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The xvii. Chapitre. ¶ An acte against vnlawful hunting in any parke, forest, chase, or other enclosed ground.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as in the first yere of your most gracious reygne your Maiestie in consideracion of the greate obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that your subiectes then were in, of youre inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable clemencie, and tendre loue borne vnto the same gaue your Roiall assente vnto an acte of parlament touching the repeale of certaine Statutes, the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whereof semed very sore, thinking moste Godlie thereby to winne your saied Subiectes, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of their obedience, rather by loue then feare, forasmuche as
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:184040:23"/> sithen the time of the saied Repeale, your grace hathe founde the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience thereof, to haue hadde other Successe, then your moste mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull meaning looked for, and that suche insolencies, and Barbarous vnrulines, and disobedience hath folowed the same, as heretofore hath not bene sene, either in this Realme, or elswhere. Amongest the whiche outragious disorders, one hath bene vnlawefull hunting, not onelye in all your Graces Subiectes seuerall groundes, but in your graces awne Parkes and Forestes, all moste through out the Realme, so notablie, as in some of your graces Parkes were slayne fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Dere in a daie within very fewe miles of your Maiesties Citie of London, whiche vnsufferable libertie escapinge without due punishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath bred suche a bolde cotinuaunce of the like, as at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sente, bothe night and daie your graces Parkes and Forestes, and the Parkes also of others are still hunted with suche boldnesse as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it is taken for a faulte, to the greate disquietnes of your graces kepers, and the destruccion of your Roiall games, beside the shame and dishonoure, that in other Realmes thereof is spoken. For refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion thereof, moste humblie besechen your grace, youre Maiesties moste humble and louing Subiectes, that it maie bee ordeined and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted, by your Maiestie, the Lordes Spirituall and Temporall, &amp; the Commons in this presente Parlamente assembled, and by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the same, that aswell one Estatute made in the Parlamente holden at westminster in the .xxxi. yere of the reigne of kinge Henrie the eyghte, touching the wrongefull entre into any Forest, Parke, or Chase, of the Kynges highnesse, the Quenes, the Princes, or any of the Kinges children, for the time being, or in to any other grounde of his, or theirs inclosed with wall, or Pale, ordeined or vsed for nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of Dere, as also one other Estatute made in the Session of the saied Parlament, holden in the .xxxii. yere of the reigne of the same late King touching the wrongefull taking, killinge, or sleing of any Dere, within any Parke, Chase, or closed grounde vsed for Dere, maie from the firste daie of Maye nexte comminge bee fully &amp; clerelye reuiued and that the same Statutes with all and all maner of braunches, arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Sentences, and Penalties of the same seuerall Estatutes, maye from the same daie be in full force, strengthe and vertue, to all ententes, constructions, and purposes, as if the same Estatutes, or any of them had neuer been repealed, the sayed Acte of repeale, or any other acte or thing to the contrarye in any wise notwithstanding. This Statute to endure the space of three full yeres to be complete and fullie ended, from the first daie of Maie abouesaied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwaies and be it enacted, that thys presente Acte or any thing therein conteined, shall not in any wise extende to cause the wife of suche Offendour or Offendours, to loose any dower, but that the wife and wiues of suche offendour and offendours, shall
<pb facs="tcp:184040:24"/> haue suche interest and recouerie of, in, and to their Dower of the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, tenemētes, and hereditaments of suche offendour and offendours, as they shoulde haue had, in case no suche attaindour or conuiction had been had of any the offences afore saied. And that by suche attainder or conuiction, the heire of suche offendour or offendours shall lose no inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce, ne suffre any corrupcion of bloude, but shall after the death of suche offendour and offendours, inherite and bee demed and adiudged as heire, and enabled as heire to suche offendour or offendours in suche maner and forme, as if no suche attaindour or conuiction had been had Any thing herein cōteined to the cōtrarie in any wise notwithstanding</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>The .xviii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte concerning Fee fermes mencioned. in the last Session.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the seconde Session of this present Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden at Westminster vpō Prorogacion the iiii. daie of Nouembre in the second yere of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> reigne of our moste dreade Souuereigne Lorde the kinge that now is: Our Souereigne Lorde the Kinge of his moste godlie and vertuous disposicion, by thas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Lordes Spirituall and Temporal, and the Commons in the saied Parlamente assembled and by aucthoritie of the same, aswell for the aide and Reliefe of the poore in the Cities, boroughes, and tounes corporate of this his realme of Englande, and countrie of Wales, as for the execucion of other dedes of charitie, and common wealthe there ordeined &amp; enacted, that suche Fee fermes and summes of moneie paied for feefermes, as by any Citie, Boroughe or Toune corporate, within this his Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, or countrie of Wales, or by the bodies politique or corporate, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or ministers of the same, shoulde or ought to bee due and payable to his Maiestie, his heires, or successours, during three yeres nexte en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing after the .xiiii. daie of Marche, in the yere of our Lorde God. M. D. xlviii. shoulde ceasse and not bee due, ne paieable to his Maiestie ne his heires, or his successours by any suche Citie, Boroughe, ne Toune corporate, ne by any the bodies politique or corporate of theim or anye of them, nor by the Officers, inhabitauntes and ministers of the same Cities, Boroughes, or Tounes corporate, or any of them, and that the saied Acte shoulde bee to theim, and euery of theim, and to the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours of euery of them, a sufficient warraunt and discharge againste his Maiestie, his heires and Successours, for the reteining and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of the same Feefermes and summes of moneie, during the saied three yeres, and that no processe or other sute shoulde be at any time had or awarded against theim, or any of theim, out of the Exchequer, or any other Courte for the Arrerages thereof, for, or in any of the sayed three yeres.</p>
            <pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:184040:24"/>
            <p>And it was then ferther prouided and enacted by the saied auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, that asmuche of all, and euery suche summes of moneie, as shoulde or ought to be due to the kinges Maiestie, his heires or successours, by any Citie, Borough, toune corporate within Englande, or wales, or by the bodies politique of the same, or by any of the officers or ministers of the same, or any of theim, during y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied three yeres, which might bee gathered and collected of the Issues, Fermes, and profeictes, for which the saied Feefermes shoulde haue be paied, in case the same had not been discharged by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied acte, shoulde be leuied, collected, gathered, paied &amp; aunswered, as it shoulde haue been, if y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied acte had not been made to be emploied and bestowed in, &amp; about repairing of walles, bridges settīg poore people on worke, or other good dedes in euery suche Citie, Borough; or Toune corporat, where the same shoulde so haue been due, during the saied three yeres, if the saied Acte had not been made, by the discrecion and apoinctment of suche Commissioners, as the Kinges Maiestie shoulde particularlie aucthorise, &amp; appoincte for euery suche Citie, Borough or toune corporate, in suche maner and fourme, as the same cōmissioners shoulde assigne, limite, and appoinct, or as by suche cōmission shoulde be declared or expressed, and not to the kinges Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, his heires or successours in his courte of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Exchequier, or in any other courte or place, to thuse of his Maiestie, his heires or successours. Neuerthelesse, for diuerse especiall cōsideracions, and weightie causes: Be it now enacted, ordeined and established, by aucthoritie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parlamente, that the saied former acte, concerning the saied Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermes and summes of moneie, and all articles, clauses, and prouisions, concerning the ordre, disposicion and paimētes of the same Feefermes and summes of moneie, or any of theim therin conteined, or of any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie or summes of monie out of thesaied Feefermes, and summes of moneie paied for Feefermes, shall stande, remaine, and bee in their full strength, power &amp; effecte, onely for the first yere of the saied three yeres conteined in the saied acte, &amp; not otherwise, ne for any longer time.</p>
            <p>And that the saied act of Feefermes, and al articles, clauses, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisions therein conteined, touching and cōcerning the remitting, retei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, disposiciō, or paiemēt of the saied feefermes, or of any part or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell thereof, of and for the last twoo yeres of the saied three yeres, shall vtterly ceasse, determine, and take none effect, any thing cōteined in the saied former acte, to the contrarie in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And furthermore be it enacted and established by thauctoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied, that from and after the .xxiii. daie of marche in this present yere, of our lorde God. M.D.xlix. the saied feefermes, and sūmes of moneie paied for Feefermes, and euery of theim, shalbe due, paiable, and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable vnto the kinges Maiestie, his heires, &amp; successours, at suche times and places, and in suche maner, forme, and condicion, to all inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, cōstructions and purposes, as the same, or any of them were, ought
<pb facs="tcp:184040:25"/> or might haue been paied, or paiable before the making of the saied for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer acte, any thing therin conteined to the contrarie thereof notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies &amp; be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that all &amp; euerie patentee or patētees, and al other persones and bodies po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique and corporate, their heires, successours and assignes, which by vertue of the letters patentes of the kinges Maiestie, or of any of his noble progenitours, or otherwise, at, and before the making of the saied former acte, had or enioied, or lawfullie shoulde, or might haue had, or enioied, any annuitie, or summe or sūmes of moneie going out, or to be takē or paieable of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied fee fermes, or sūmes of moneie paied for fee fermes, or any of thē, shal &amp; maie lawefully claime, aske, demaūde, haue, and enioie suche annuitie or summes of moneie, as shalbe due, paiable, and aunswerable to any suche patētee or patentees, or any other perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or bodies politique &amp; corporat, their heires, successours, &amp; assignes, or any of them, from and after the saied .xiiii. daie of Marche, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied yere of our lord God. M.D.xlix. at suche times and places, and in suche sorte, maner and fourme, to all intentes and purposes, as the same annuitie or summe or sūmes of moneie were paied or aunswered at, &amp; before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> making of the saied former acte, and in none otherwise, any thing herein cōteined to the cōtrarie thereof in any wise not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xix. Chapiter. ¶ An acte for the buiyng and selling or roather beastes and Cattal.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by the auctoritie of this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, that no persone nor persones, at any time frō and after the feast of the Annunciacion of our Ladie nexte comming, shal buie, or common, and cōclude to buie, any maner of Oxen, Steres, ron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, kien, heighfers, or calues, but onely in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> open faire or market, where the same shall happen to be brought and put to sale, and shal not sell the same againe on liue at and in the market or faire, where he bought the same during the time of the saied faire or market, vpon peine of forfeicture of the double value of suche cattall bought or solde, contrarie to the tenour of this present acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaie and be it ferther enacted by the aucthoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied, that it shalbe lawefull for all and euery persone and persones, to buie any Oxen, Steres, Runtes, Kien, Heighfers, and Calues, or any of theim, out of any open faire, or market, for his or their prouision, for their housholde, teme, or dairie, at his or their will, or pleasure, to bee imploied, and spente onely in keping and maintenaunce of his or their house, or for their Teme or Dairie, and not otherwise.</p>
            <p>And be it ferther enacted, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aucthoritie abouesaied, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:184040:25"/> being a Butcher, and vsing the crafte or mistery of butcherie, shall at any time after the saied feast buie any fatte oxen, steres, rontes, kine, heighfers, calues, or shepe, and selle, or cause to be solde thesame againe on liue, vpon peine of forfeicture of euery suche oxe, stere, Ronte, Cowe, Heighfer, Calues, or shepe, bargained, or solde contrarie to the forme of this present acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaie, that all, and euery persone, and persones beyng a Butcher, and vsing theart, and misterie of Butcherie, shal and maie at his, and their will, and pleasure buy any fat oxen, steres, Runtes, Kien, heighfors, calues, and sheepe, or any of them, out of any open faire, or market: So that such butcher sel not, nor cause to be solde thesame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine on liue, as is aforesaied, any thing conteined in this acte to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie not withstanding. Thone moitie of all wiche forfeictures, shalbe to our Souereigne lorde the king, his heires, and Successours: and thother moitie to him, or theim that will sue for thesame in any of the kinges Courtes of Recorde, wherin no wager of lawe, essoine, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection shalbe allowed for the defendaunt or defendauntes. This acte to endure to thende of the nexte parlament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xx. Chapiter. ¶ An acte touching the repeale of a certaine braunche of an acte passed in the last Session of this parlament, concerning victuallers and Artificers</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here by a certeine acte made in the Parlamēt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at westminster by prorogacion the .iiii. daie of Nouembre, in the seconde yere of the reigne of our most dread souereigne lorde the king that now is, it is enacted, and established, that no persō, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sōs should at any time after the first day of Aprill thē next ēsuing, interrupt, denighe, let, or disturbe any fre Masō, Rough Masō, Carpēter, brickelaier Plaisterer, Ioiner, Hardehewer, Sawier, Tiler, Pauier, glaster limeburner, brickmaker, tilemaker, plummer, or labourer borne in this realme, or made denizen, to worke in any of the saied craftes in any citie borough, or toune corporate, with any persō, &amp; persōs, that wil reteine him, or thē, albeit the saied persō, or persons so reteined, or any of thē do not inhabit, or dwel in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> citie, boroughe, and toune corporat, where he or they shal worke, nor be free of the same citie, boroughe, or toune, any Statute, lawe, ordinaunce, or other thing what soeuer before hadde, or made to the contrarie, in any wise not withstanding, and that vpon peine of forfeicture of fiue. l. for euery interupcion, or disturbaunce doen contrarie to thesaid Estatute, thone moitie of euery suche forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be to the king, &amp; thother moitie therof to be to him, or them that
<pb facs="tcp:184040:26"/> will sue for thesame in any of the Kinges courtes of Recorde, by bille, plaint, action of debt, or informacion, wherin no wager of law, essoine, nor proteccion shoulde bee allowed, as by the saied acte of Parlamente emonges other thinges more plainely appeareth.</p>
            <p>And forasmuche as in the citie of London being the kinges cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, and most auncient citie of this realme, the artificers, and Craftes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the artes, craftes, and misteries afore saied, are at great costes, &amp; charges, aswell in bearing, and paiyng of taxes, tallages, Subsidies, Scot, Lot, and other charges, aswell to the kinges Maiestie, as to the saied citie, and at manie and sondrie triumphes and other times for the kinges honour, and that if Forreines should come, and worke emonges theim, within the liberties of the saied citie, contrarie to their auncient priuileges, that the same should be a great decaie of conning, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouerishment, and driuing awaie of the fre men, being artificers of the Craftes, and Artes, and misteries aforesaied, within the saied Citie of London, to the great hurt, or destruccion of the saied Citie.</p>
            <p>For reformacion wherof, the kinges maiestie is pleased, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that it be enacted by thaucthoritie of this present parlament, with the assent of the Lordes Spirituall, and Temporall, and the commons in this present parlament assembled, that the saied acte onelie touching tharticle, and clause aforesaied, and al, &amp; euerie sentence, and braunche conteined in the saied acte, concerning thesame article, shal fromhens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth be resumed, repealed, adnulled, reuoked, adnihilated, &amp; vtterlie made voide for euer. Any thing cōteined in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied former acte touching the clause, or article aforsaide, in any wise to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōtrarie notwithstāding</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxi. Chapiter. An Acte for the buiyng, and selling of Butter, and Chese.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by thaucthoritie of this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamēt, that no persone, or persones, after the feast of the Annunciaciō of our Ladie nexte comming, shall buie to sel againe any butyre, or chese, onlesse he or they sel y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same againe by retaile, in opē shop faire, or market, and not in grosse, vpō pein of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faicture of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> double value of thesame Butter, &amp; Chese so solde, cōtrarie to the tenour of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent acte: thone moitie of al whiche forfeictures to be to our souereigne lorde the king, his heires, and successours, and the other moitie to him, or theim that will sue for thesame in any of the kinges courtes of record wherin no wager of lawe, essoine, or proteccion shalbe allowed for the defendaunt, or defendauntes.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by the authoritie aforesaied, that the saied worde of retaile mencioned in this acte, shalbe expounded
<pb n="xxiiii" facs="tcp:184040:26"/> declared and takē, onely where a weight of Cheese, or a barrel of butter or of lesse quantitie, and not aboue shalbee solde at one time to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone or persones in open shop, faire, or market, and that to be doen with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fraude or couine.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaie, that this acte or any thing therin conteined shall not extende to any Inholder or victailer for suche butter or Cheese, as shalbe spent, or vttered by retaile, in any of their houses, any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in this acte to the contrarie notwithstanding: this act to endure to the nexte Parlament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte touching the retaining of Iourneimen by diuerse persones.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as many yong folkes and seruauntes of sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie occupaciōs, being once out of their apprēnce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hodes, or their yerelie reteined seruice, will not commonlie be reteined in seruice by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yere, nor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure in their Sciēces, Occupacions, or Craftes wherein thei bee exercised or brought vp, but at their libertie, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> daie, weke, or otherwise, worke by great, to thintent they will liue idlie &amp; at their pleasure, flie and resorte from place to place, whereof ensue more incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences then can be at this present expressed and declared.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted by the aucthoritie of this Parlament, that no persone nor persones occupiyng or vsing, or that hereafter shal occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie or vse any of the artes, misteries, occupacions, craftes or sciences of a clothemaker, fuller, shermā, weiuer, tailor or shomaker, shal after the feast of Pentecoste nexte comming, hire or reteine to woorke in any of their artes, misteries, occupacions, craftes, or Sciences, any persone or persones vnmaried, as a Iourneiman, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to saie, to worke or labor by the daie or taile worke, or by the great, or for any time or terme, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the time &amp; terme of one whole quarter of one whole yere. And that no persone nor persones vnmaried shalbe hired or reteined with any of the persone or persones aforesaied, to worke in any of the artes, miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, occupaciōs, craftes, or sciences aforesaied, for any lesse time, thē for the space of one whole quarter of one whole yere, vpon peine of euery persone offending contrarie to this Statute to suffer imprisonment for one whole moneth without baile or mainprise, &amp; to forfeicte for euery suche offence .xl.s̄.</p>
            <p>And be it enacted by thauctoritie aforesaied that euery iourneiman of any the craftes, occupaciōs or misteries aforesaied, being required by any persone or persones vsing the misteries, occupacions, craftes or sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences aforesaied, or any of them, to serue by the quarter of the yere, halfe yere, or whole yere vpon suche reasonable wages as betwene thē shalbe agreed, &amp; in case where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parties cannot accord, thē for such wages as
<pb facs="tcp:184040:27"/> shalbe adiudged &amp; decreed by one Iustice of the peace, maior, aldermā, Bailife, Portreue, Constable, or tithing man of the Shire, Citie, toune borough, village, hundred, wapētake, or tithing, where any suche Iur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neiman shalbe required to serue, as is abouesaied, &amp; there vpō if suche Iourneman refuse to serue in maner and fourme abouesaied, that then euery suche Iourneiman and euery of them so refusing to serue, as is abouesaied, shall suffer imprisonment, by the space of one whole moneth and shall at euery time so refusing forfeict. xx.s̄.</p>
            <p>And be it ferther enacted, that al and euery person or persons, that shal haue .iii. aprentices in any of the saied craftes, misteries, or occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, shal reteine &amp; kepe one Iourneiman, and for euery other apprē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice aboue the numbre of thesaied .iii. apprentices one other iournemā vpon peine for euery default .x.l. the one halfe of al whiche forfeictures, shalbe to the kyng our Souereigne lorde, and thother half to suche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone or persones, as wil sue for thesame in any of the kinges courtes of Recorde, by bill, informacion, accion of debt, or otherwise, in whiche suit no essoine, proteccion, or wager of lawe, shalbe admitted or allowed.</p>
            <p>And it is ferther enacted by thauctoritie abouesaied, that al and singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar thoffences abouesaied, whiche shalbe hereafter cōmitted or doen, contrarie to the tenour of this present acte, shalbe inquirable &amp; presenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Iustices of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Determiner,</hi> Iustices of Assises, Iusticez of the Peace, and in all and euery lete or letes, before the Stewarde or stewardes there, and before any Maior, bailife, or other head officer, of any Citie, Toune, or borough corporat, and that the saied Iustices, ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, Maiour, Bailife, or other head officer, shal haue full power and aucthoritie from time to time to punishe and correcte, all and euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone and persones offending contrarie to the tenour of this present act, according to suche presentment or presentmentes, as before him or thē shalbe had or made.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, &amp; be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that all seruauntes of husbandrie vnmaried, and whiche haue not been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and all seruauntes and labourers vsing to labour in barges com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie called Westerne barges, which are not, nor haue been maried, shall after the feast of the Annunciacion of our Ladie next comming, serue by the hole yere and not goe by the daie wages, vpō peine of suche punishment as is conteined in the Statutes made against labourers, and that all suche seruauntes shall after thesaied feast geue their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster &amp; Maistresse a quarters warning, against his, or their departure out of seruice vpon the like peine conteined in thesaied Statute.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xxiii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte concerning the release of the braunches in the last acte of the Reliefe, for the paimentes of shepe and Clothes, and also of a graunt of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidie to be paied in one yere.</head>
            <pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:184040:27"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oste humble praing the Communs in this present Parlemente assambled, your moste excellēt maiestie, that where in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> last Sessiō of this present Parlament vpon prorogation, begō at Westminster the .iiii. daie of Nouēbre, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> second yere of your highnesse reigne, and there continued vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> .xiiii. daie of Marche thē next folowīg, your hūble, &amp; faithfull Subiectes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mōs, in the saied parlament assembled, with thassent of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and temporal, graunted vnto your highnesse one relief of .iii.s̄. of euery l. of the goodes, and Cattals, of euery persone beyng woorth .x,l. &amp; vpwarde, to be leuied, &amp; taken in .iii. yeres, in maner, and forme as is mentioned in thesaid acte. And also one other relief, to be taken &amp; leuied, for euery shere shepe, accompting y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same by the polle, after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rate, as by thesame acte more at large it doth appere. And one other relief of viii.d of the .l. of the price, and value of all, and singuler wollen Clothes to be taxed, and leuied, in maner, and forme, as by thesame acte is declared: Thesame seueral reliefes to endure, and to be yerelie paied, and leuied during thre yeres, as by the same former acte, more largelie it appereth: whiche Relief of Clothe apperethe now, so comberous to all Clothma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, &amp; also so tedious to thesame, for makinge, of their bookes and the accomptes therof, by reason of lacke of the alnagers not alwaies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sēt, whē time requireth, that in maner thei are discouraged to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cloth, or to set any mē on worke about thesame: and also the said re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of shepe is to your poore commons, hauing but few shepe in nombre a great charge, and also so comberous for all your Commissioners, and officers, named, and appointed for executing of the same, that thei can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tel, how to serue your highnesse ther in according to their dueties It maie therfore please your highnesse, with thassent of the lordes spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and Temporal and of your saied Commōs, and at their moste humble sute, that it be enacted, by the aucthoritie of this present parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the seueral graunts, and clauses, mencioned in the said acte of reliefe, concerning or touching onely the seuerall grauntes of Relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes to bee leuied, and paied for shepe after the rate of the polle, and of clothe to be paied, or of any of them, as in the former act is recited, and euery article, clause, prouision, and sentence, concerning onely the same seueral grauntes of reliefes for shepe, and clothe, or either of thē, shalbe from the said .iiii. daie of Nouembre, in the said second yere of your most noble riegne, deined &amp; adiudged voide, and of none effect, and to be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie repealed, to al intentes, constructions, and purposes. And that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery article, clause, and prouision mencioned in thesaied acte of reliefe, touching, or concerning the relief, of, and for gooddes, to stande, and be good, and effectual, according to the tenor of thesame act of relief. And we your humble, &amp; obedient Subiectes, beseche your highnesse, that it
<pb facs="tcp:184040:28"/> maie please your highnesse, to take, and receiue of vs your said subiectes towardes your inestimable charges, that you haue alreadie susteined and borne, and be lyke herafter to susteyne, and beare, for the defence of vs, and this your highnesse realme, and dominions, against tholde, and auncient enemies of the same, the Frenchemen, and the Scottes, nowe beyng open enemies to your highnesse, your saied realme, &amp; dominions this small gyft hereafter folowing, not as any recompence, or satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to your maiestie, of, and for your most bountifull, and liberall relesse, and dyscharge of your sayed humble subiectes, of, and concernyng the sayed seuerall reliefes of shepe, and clothes, but as a token, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our faithfulnesse, louing, and willyng hartes, towardes your highnesse, to be alwaies readie, to beare with your highnesse, to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost of our powers, in all your procedynges, and affaires, as to the duetie of naturall, &amp; obedient subiectes apperteineth: that is to say: we your graces saied louing subiectes, dooe, by aucthoritie of thys present parlament, frely, and of our good hartes, and myndes, geue, and graūt vnto your most royall maiestie, one other reliefe, to continue by one yere next ensuing the determination of the sayed three yeres specified in the sayed former acte of reliefe, for goodes to be rated, taxed, leuied, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered of euery persone, of what estate or degree he be, accordyng to the tenour of thys acte after the rate, and in maner, and fourme folowyng, that is to saye, aswell of all, and euery persone, as is, or herafter shalbe, your graces natural subiectes, as of all, and euery Fraternitie, Guilde, Corporation, Misterie, Brotherhod, Compaignie, and Commonaltie, corporate, or not corporate, within this Realme of Englande, Wales, and other the kynges dominions, beyng woorth .x. pounde of money, Coygne, plate, stocke of merchandise, Corne, Grayne, shepe, Beastes, cattals, or other goodes moueable, aswel within this realme, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, &amp; of all such sūmes of money, as to him or thē shalbe owing, wherof he, or they trust in theyr consciences surely to be paied .xii.d. of euery li. And of euery alien, or straunger, borne out of the kynges obeysaunce, aswel denisen, as not denisen, inhabiting, or resiant within this realme or any other the kinges dominions, being worth .x.li. in money, coigne, Plate, stocke of Merchaundise, Corne, Grayne, sheepe, Beastes, Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, or other goodes moueable, aswell within this realme, as without, and of all such summes of money, as to him is, or shalbe owing, wherof he trusteth in his conscience to be surely paied .ii.s̄. of euerye li. And of euery Alien, or straunger, borne out of the kynges obeysaunce, aswell Denison, as not denison, inhabiting, or resiaunt within this realme, or any other the kinges dominions, beyng woorth .xx.s. and vnder .x.li. in money, coygne, Plate, stocke of Merchaundise, Corne, Grayne, shepe, beastes, cattall, or other goodes moueable, aswell within this realme as without, and of all suche summes of money, as to hym, is, or shalbe owing, wherof he trusteth in hys conscience to be surely payed .xii.d. of
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:184040:28"/> euery pounde. Except, &amp; out of the premisses deducted, suche summes of Money, as any persone or persones before chargeable owe, and in hys or their conscience truly mynde to pay. And excepted also the apparell of such persones, their wiues, &amp; chyldren, belongyng to their awne bodies, sauyng Iewelles, golde, syluer, Stone, and Pearle. Excepted also al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies from the charge, Assessement, and payment of the saied reliefe, all money, gooddes, and Cattals of orphanes, bequethed or left vnto them by their parentes, or other their Frendes deceassed. And that all Plate, coigne, Iewelles, gooddes, debtes, and cattalles personal, being in the rule and custodie of any persone, or persones, to the vse of anye Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion, Fraternitie, Guilde, Misterie, Brotherhead, Companye, or any Commonaltie beyng corporate, or not corporate, be and shalbe rated, set, and charged, by reason of this acte, at the value certified by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentours of the certificat, to be sworne of euery pounde in gooddes and debtes, as is aboue saied, and the summes that are before rehearsed, set and taxed, to be leuied and takē of them, that shal haue such gooddes in custodie, as is before rehearsed. And the same persone or persones, and bodie corporate, by the aucthoritie of thys acte, shalbe dyscharged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst him or them, that shall, or ought to haue the same, at the tyme of the payment, or deliuerie therof, or at his otherwise departure from the custodie, or possessiō of the same. Excepted alwaies &amp; foreprised from the charge and assessemēt of this reliefe, all gooddes, cattals, Iewels, and ornamentes of churches and chapelles, ordeyned and vsed in churches or chapelles, for diuine seruice therin to be celebrated.</p>
            <p>Also we the kinges maiesties louing and obediēt subiectes, doe geue and graunt to your highnesse .viii.d. to be paied in thesame yere by euery other persone not borne vnder the kynges obeisaunce, beyng Denizen, or not denizen, other then women couert, souldiours, and such persones as be vnder the age of .xii. yeres, dwelling or resiant within thys realme or any other the kynges dominions. And the sayed Reliefes shalbe, by auctoritie aforesaied, taxed, assessed, and rated in the sayed yere, in euery Shire, Ridyng, Lath, Wapentake, Rape, citie, borough, towne, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery other place, within thys realme of Englande, and Wales, &amp; other the kinges dominions, in fourme following, that is to say, before the .xx. day of Ianuary, which shalbe in the yere of our Lorde God. M.D.Li. &amp; the paiment therof to be had, made, &amp; paied at the receipt of the kinges Exchequier, betwene the fyrst daye, &amp; the .xx. day of Aprill, whiche shall be in the yere of our lord God. M.D.Lii. And the sūmes abouesayed, of and for the saied reliefe, shalbe taxed, set, asked, &amp; demaūded, taken, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, leuied, &amp; paied, vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vse of our saied souereigne lord, his heires and successours, in fourme aboue saied, aswell within Liberties, fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheses, Sanctuaries, auncient demeasne, and other whatsoeuer place exempte, or not exempte, as without. Excepte suche shires, places, and persones as shalbe foreprised, in, and by this present acte, anye graunt,
<pb facs="tcp:184040:29"/> charter, prescripcton, vse or libertie, by reason of any letters patentes, or other priuilege, prescripciō, allowance of the same, or whatsoeuer other matter of discharge heretofore to the contrary made, graunted, vsed, or obteyned, notwithstandyng. And it is ferther enacted, by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this present Parlament, that euery such persone, aswell suche as be borne vnder the kynges obeysaunce, as euery other persone straūger borne, denizen, or not denizen, inhabiting within this realme or within Wales, or other the kynges dominions, whiche at the tyme of the sayed assessing, or taxacion to be had or made, shalbe out of thys realme and out of Wales, and haue gooddes or Cattalles within this realme or in Wales, shalbe charged and chargeable for the same, by the certificat of thinhabitauntes of the parties where such gooddes, cattalles, or other the premisses then shalbe, or in such other place, where suche persone, or hys factor, deputie, or attourney, shall haue hys most resort vnto, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realme, or in Wales, in lyke maner, as if thesame persone were, or had been, at the tyme of thesame assessement, within thys Realme, or wales. And that euery persone abyding within thys realme, or without thys realme, shalbe charged and chargeable to the same reliefe graūted by this acte, accordyng and after the rate of the value of hys substaūce, gooddes, &amp; cattalles, &amp; other premysses, as suche persone so to be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, shalbe set at, in the tyme of the sayed assessing or taxacion, vpō them to be made, and in none otherwyse.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alway, and be it ferther enacted, by auctoritie aboue sayed, that all and euery taxacion, and assessement of the saied relief for good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or for any former graunt, or subsidie heretofore had, made, graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or taxed (foreprised, and excepted the saied seuerall reliefes, for shepe and clothe, and eyther of them) shalbe takē, iudged, and demed, of good force, strength, and effecte, to all intentes, constructions, and purposes, and shalbe leuied and paied to your highnesse accordyngly.</p>
            <p>And be it ferther enacted, by the aucthoritie aboue sayed, that the lorde Chauncellour of Englande, or the lorde keper of the great Seale for the tyme beyng, the Commyssioners in that behalfe, by the Kynges Commission to be appoincted, and aucthorised, the presentours, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone presented, chargeable, or taxed, Collectours, petit Collectours, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the kinges Exchequer, Auditours, and all and euery other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone and persones, mencioned in the saied former acte of Reliefe, shall by auctoritie of this present act, make, doe, and execute all and euery thing and thinges, concerning the sayed reliefe graunted by this present acte, as is conteyned, limitted, and appoyncted to them by the sayed former acte of Reliefe for gooddes, and vpon lyke peynes, fynes, amerciamētes and forfeyctures, and in such and the same maner, fourme, estate, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion, to all intentes, constructions, &amp; purposes, as they or any of them are appoincted, myght, may, shoulde, or ought to doe, &amp; execute by auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the sayed former acte, touching the relief for gooddes, and as
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:184040:29"/> though euery clause, article, sentence, and matter mencioned in the saied former acte, concerning or touching the sayed Reliefe for gooddes, were specially and particularly recited, and mencioned in this present acte.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwaies, that this graunt of Reliefe, nor any other thyng therein conteined, doe in any wise extende, to charge the inhabitauntes or dwellers within Irelande, Bullome, and the coūtie of the same, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Hāmes, Guysnes, &amp; the marches of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, Iernesey, &amp; Gernesey, Alderney, and Silleye, or any of them, of, for, or cōcerning any goodes, whiche the sayed inhabitauntes, or dwellers, or anye other to their vse, haue within Irelande, Bulloin, the coūtie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, Calice, Hammes, Guisnes, or other marches of the same, Ierneseye, Gernesey, Alderneie, and Silleye, or in any of them.</p>
            <p>Prouyded also that the sayed graunt of reliefe, doe not in any maner of wyse extende, or be preiudiciall or hurtefull to the inhabitauntes, or Resiauntes at this present tyme, within the fyue Portes Corporate, or to any of theyr membres incorporate, or vnited to the same fiue Portes, or to any of the same fiue Portes, or to any of the inhabitauntes within the liberties of Romney Mershe, of, or for any part or parcel of the sayed summes graunted in this present Parlament, of the saied inhabitaūtes now resiantes, or any of them to be taxed, set, asked, leuied, or paied, but that the sayed inhabitauntes, and nowe resiauntes of the sayed Portes of Romney mershe, and theyr membres, and of euery of them, be, and shalbe of, and from the sayed graunt and payment of the sayed Reliefe, during theyr resiauncie there, and not longer, acquited and discharged, any matter, or whatsoeuer thing in this present act, made, or had, to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouyded also, that this present acte of Reliefe, ne any other thyng therin conteined, extende to any of the Englyshe inhabitauntes, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siauntes in any of the Counties of Northumberlande, Comberlande, Westmorlande, the toune of Barwike, the towne of Newecastell vpon Tyne, and the Byshoprike of Duresme, nor to anye of them, of, for, and concerning any gooddes, or Cattalles, whiche the same inhabitauntes or dwellers, or any other to theyr vse, haue within the sayed Counties, of Northumberlande, Cumberlande, and Westmorlande, or the toune of Barwike, the Towne of Newcastle vpon Tyne, or the Byshoprike of Duresme, or any of them, but that they, and euerye of them shalbe of, and for their gooddes lying and beyng in the sayed counties, Tounes, and Bishoprike, or of anye of them, vtterlye acquyted and dyscharged, any thing in this present act before rehearsed, to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded also, that thys Acte, ne any thing therein conteined, shall extende to the gooddes of anye College, Halle, or Hostle, within the Vniuersities of Oxforde &amp; Cambridge, or any of them, or to the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the College of Winton founded by Byshop Wickham, or to the
<pb facs="tcp:184040:30"/> goodes of the College of Eton next Windesore, or to the goodes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Reader, or Scholer within the saied Vniuersities, and colleges, or any of them there remaining for studie, without fraude, or couine, anye thing in this acte conteined to the contrarye in anye wyse notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and bee it enacted by the auctoritie aforesayed, that al, and euery collectour, petite Collectour, and other persone, and persons, that haue leuied, gathered, or receiued any summe, or summes of moneie of any person, or persons, for the Relief of Shepe, and clothe, or either of them, shall before the last daie of Februarie next comminge, repaie, and deliuer to euery soche persone and persons, his, or their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutours, or administratours, al, and euery thesame sūme, and sūmes of money so by them, or any of them receiued, vpō peyne of forfeicture dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the value of euery such summe, or sūmes of money so by them, or any of thē receiued, &amp; not repaied before the saied last day of Februarye. For the which forfaiture, the partie greued, shall, and maye haue his reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye by accion of debt, byll, playnt, or informacion, in anye of the kynges courtes of Recorde, where no wager of lawe, essome, or protection shall be allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouyded also, and be it enacted, by the sayed aucthoritie, that all &amp; syngular sūmes of money, as now be, or hereafter shalbe payed by anye collectour, or petit collectour, or other persone to the kynges vse in hys receipte, or elswhere, for the reliefes of Shepe, and clothe, or eyther of them, shalbe deliuered, &amp; repaied to the sayed collectour, his executours, or administratours, at, &amp; vpon his, or theyr request in the sayed receipt, to the vses, and intentes aboue saied, and that thys act shall be a suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent warraunt to thofficers of the kinges receipte, to repaye and deliuer the same to the saied Collectour, hys Executours, or administratours, without any farther, or other warrant to be sued for, to the kinges high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>Prouyded also, and be it enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that thys act of graunt of reliefe, shall not extende to anye spirituall persone or persones, for any of his, or theyr gooddes, or cattalles: and forasmuch as diuers and sundry the kynges Maiesties tenauntes, and other the inhabitauntes, &amp; dwellers within the counties of Penbroke, Carmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Cardigan, Glamorgā, Brecknock, Radnor, Moūtgomery, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigh, Flynt, Merioneth, Anglesey, Carnaruan, and of the countie Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentine of Chester, be at thys present tyme charged, &amp; chargeable with the seuerall paiementes of diuers great summes of money by the name of a Mise due to his maiestie accordyng to the seuerall customes of the sayed counties, for the paiement wherof, dyuers &amp; sundry the gentlemē, and other inhabitauntes of the sayed counties, be, and stand bounde to hys hyghnesse: The king our souereygne lorde is therfore pleased, and contented, that it be prouyded, ordeyned, and enacted by thaucthoritie
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:184040:30"/> afore saied, that this Acte or any thinge therein conteined, shall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to charge anye of the kynges maiesties tenauntes, and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes, and dwellers, within any of the sayed counties, of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke, Carmarthen, Cardigā, Glamorgā, Brecknock, Radnor, Moūt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomerie, Denbigh, Flynt, Merioneth, Anglesey, Carnaruan, and the countie of the Palantine of Chester, beeyng charged, or chargeable, with the sayed Mise, for, or within any of the paymentes of the saied re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief graunted to the kinges maiestie by this acte, or by the saied former acte, vntill the seuerall daies, and tymes appointed, &amp; graunted, for the paymētes of the sayed Mises shalbe expired. And that the first paymēt of the sayed relief graunted by this acte, and the sayed former acte, shall be made at the receipte of the kinges Exchequer, before the fyrst day of Maye then next following, after the daye appoincted for the latter pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be made of the sayed Mise, and so yerely, before the first daye of Maye, at the receipte of the sayed Exchequer, vntyll the foure seuerall paymentes of the sayed relief be fully made, in suche, and lyke fourme, &amp; ordre, as is ordeyned, &amp; appoynted by this acte, and by the sayed former acte for the Kynges subiectes, concernyng the sayed Reliefe to be made at the receipte of the sayed Exchequer, accordyng to the tenour of thys present acte, and of the sayed former acte. Thys acte, and the sayed former acte, or any thing in them, or eyther of them conteined, to the contrary, in any wise not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:184040:31"/>
            <pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:184040:31"/>
            <head>¶ AN ACTE OF THE KINGES MAIESTIES MOSTE FREE and generall pardon. ¶ The .xxiiii. Chapitre.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE kinges most Roiall Maiestie right well percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uīg his louing subiectes by many, and sondrie waies and meanes, greuouslie against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bounden duties of their allegeaunces, to haue now of late this last som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time offēded his highnesse, and his lawes, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate disobedience, rebellion, and otherwise, &amp; his maiestie by goddes prouidence beīg replenished with mercie, clemencie, and pitie, &amp; muche enclined to allure, prouoke, and styrre his saied louing subiectes to loue obedience, which to them of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie apperteineth, his maiestie hauing a speciall trust, &amp; confidence in his sayed subiectes, that they will herafter applye, and indeuour themselues to serue, and please hym in all obedience, and obseruance of his lawes, which hys highnesse willeth, and chargeth them to doe, lest vpon suche like disobedience, rebellion, and other offences, hys highnesse shalbe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, and constreigned to execute his seuere iustice, which to hys im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall, and Kyngly estate, and function doeth apperteyne, and maye, nor will no lenger beare, and susteyne herafter any such rebellion, being a great peryll to hys graces persone, and clere subuersion, and a likelye destruction of hys saied realme, and Subiectes, and a great comforte to all his graces enemies: is fully, and resolutely contented, and pleased that it be enacted by aucthoritie of thys present Parlament, in maner, and fourme folowing. That is to say, that all &amp; euery of hys sayed sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, aswell spirituall, as temporall, of thys hys realme of Englande, Wales, the Isles of Iernesey, and Gernesey, Barwicke, Calleis, Guis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Hammes, Bulloigne, and Bulloignois, and the marches of euery of them, Theyres, successours, executours, and administratours of thē, and euerye of them, and all and syngular bodies in anye maner of wyse corporate, Cities, Boroughes, shyres, Ridynges, Hundredes, Lathes, Rapes, Wapentakes, Townes, Vyllages, and Tythinges, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, and the Successour, and Successours of them, and euerye of them, shalbe by thaucthoritie of thys present Parlament, acquyted, perdoned, released, and dyscharged against the Kynges hyghnesse, hys Heyres, successours, and Executours, and euery of them, of all maner of Heresies, Treasons, rebellions, Insurrections, vnlawfull assemblies, Conuenticles, Conspiracies, Misprisions of Treason, Concealemētes of Treason, Murdres, Fellonies, Robberies, Offences, Contemptes, Trespasses, Wronges, Deceiptes, Misdemeanours, Forfaictures, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, Sommes of money, Paines of Death, Peines Corporall, and Pecuniarie, &amp; all other thinges, Causes, Quereles, Sutes, iudgemēts
<pb facs="tcp:184040:32"/> and executions, which may be, or can be by his hyghnes in any wise, or by any meanes perdoned, or released, or dyscharged, before, &amp; vnto the xxii. day of Ianuary, in the yere of our lord God. M.D.xlix. other then suche as hereafter in this acte be excepted, and foreprised, in such maner and fourme, and vnto suche tymes as the same be excepted, or forprised in thys acte, and other then such as the clauses of prouiso hereafter mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned, doe, or doeth extende vnto.</p>
            <p>And also the kynges highnesse is further contented, and pleased, that it be enacted by thaucthoritie of thys present parlament, that this hys sayed general, and free pardon shalbe as good, and effectual in the law, to euery of hys sayed subiects, bodies corporate, and other before reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and to euery of them by the saied generall wordes before rehersed in all thinges, which be not herafter in this present acte excepted, or forpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, nor conteined in anye clause of prouiso herafter mencioned, as that same pardon should be if all offences, contemptes, forfaictures, causes, matters, suites, quereles, iudgementes, executions, penalties, and all other thinges not herafter excepted, nor conteyned in any clause of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiso herafter mencioned, had been particularlye, singularlye, specially, &amp; plainely named, rehearsed, and specified in thys present acte, &amp; also par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by propre, and expresse wordes, and names, in theyr kyndes, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and qualities, by woordes and termes therunto requisite to haue be put in, &amp; expressed in this act of free pardone. And that his sayed sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, nor any of thē, nor theires, executours, or administratours of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, nor any of the saied bodies corporate, nor any other persons, bodies politique, or corporate before named, or any of them be, nor shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be sued, vexed, or inquieted, in theyr bodies, goodes, lādes, or cattalles, for any maner matter, cause, contempt, mysdemeanor, forfaycture, tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe, offence, or anye other thyng, suffred, doen, or commytted agaynst his highnes, or his croune, dignitie, prerogatiue, lawes, or statutes, but onely for, or concerning such matters, clauses, and offences, as be reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, or mencioned in thexcepcions, or clauses of prouiso in thys present acte hereafter mencioned, in such maner, and fourme, as in the same ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepcions, or clauses of prouiso be mencioned, and for none other: Anye statute, or statutes, lawes, customes, vses, or presidentes hertofore had, made, or vsed to the contrarye in any wise notwithstandyng. And that all, and euerye the kynges saied subiectes, and all, and singular bodies corporate, and other before rehearsed, may by hym, or them selues, or by his, or their deputie, or deputies, or by his, or their attorney, or attorneis according to the lawes of this realme, pleade, &amp; minister this present act of free pardō for his, or their discharge, of, and for euery thing that is by vertue of thys present acte pardoned, dyscharged, geuen, or graunted, without any fee, or other thing in any wise paying to anye persō, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones for wryting, or entrie of the iugement, or other cause concernyng
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:184040:32"/> suche plee, writing, or entrie, but onely .xii.d. to be paied to the officer, or clerke, that shall entre the plee, matter, or iudgemēt, for the discharge of any partie so pleading thesame: any statute, lawe, or vse to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, the kynges hyghnesse is pleased, and contented, that it be enacted by thaucthoritie of thys present parlament, that thys hys saied free pardō by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> generall wordes before rehersed, shalbe repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, demed, and iudged, allowed, and taken in all maner of courtes, or elswhere, aswell in the woordes, and clauses of exceptions, and forpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses specifyed in thys present acte, as in all, and singular other clauses, woordes, and sentences mencioned, and rehearsed in this his saied free pardone most beneficially, and auaileably to all, and singular hys saied subiectes, bodies corporate, and other before rehearsed, and to euery of them in all thinges ambiguous, and doubtfull, &amp; most strongly in barre and dyscharge against his highnesse, his heires, successours, and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours in euery thing without obstacle, chalenge, or other delay whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it shalbe, to be made, pleaded, obiected, or alledged by the kyng our souereigne lorde, his heyres, successours, or executours, or by hys, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their generall attourney, or attourneyes, or by any persone, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones for his highnes, or any of his heyres, successours, or executours.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, it is enacted by the kyng our Souereygne Lorde, by thaucthoritie of thys present parlament, that if any officer, or Clerke of any of his highnesse courtes commonly called the kynges bench, the Chaūcerie, the cōmon place, or exchequier, or any other officer, or clerke of any other court within thys realme, or Wales, or other hys highnesse dominions aboue mencioned, at any time after the last day of Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, in the yere of our Lord God. M.D.xlix. make out, or write out any maner of writtes, or other processe, or any extractes, summones, or other preceptes, whereby any of the saied subiects, or any of the sayed bodies corporate, or other before rehearsed, or anye of them shalbe in anye wyse arrested, attached, dystreined, summoned, or otherwise vexed, inquieted or greued in his, or their bodies, lādes, tenemētes, gooddes, or cattals, or in any of thē, for, or because of any maner of thyng pardoned or dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by vertue of this acte of free pardon, he so offending, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of lawfully condemned, shall yelde, and paye for the recompence therof to the partie so greued, or offēded, treble damages, the costes of his sute to be accoūpted, as parcell of the damages. And neuerthelesse, all &amp; sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular suche writtes, proces, extractes, and preceptes so to be made, for, or vpon any maner thyng pardoned, or dyscharged by this acte of free pardone, shalbe vtterly voyde, and of none effecte.</p>
            <p>Except alwayes, and forprised of this generall, and free pardone, all &amp; all maner prepensed, &amp; wilfull murder, and all, and euery robbery cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or doen in, or nere the high way, &amp; all, and euery wilfull burning of any house, or barne with corne, and all, and euery offence of burgula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb facs="tcp:184040:33"/> robbyng of churches, or chappelles, dooen, or perpetrated sithen the feast of Sainct Michael tharchangel last past.</p>
            <p>And also except, and forprised out of this free pardon, all, and all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of piracies, had, doen, committed, or perpetrate vpon, or in the seas.</p>
            <p>And also excepted, and forprised out of thys free pardone, all, and all maner of punishmētes, impeticions, forfaitures, peines of death, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and executions for the premisses before excepted, or for anye of them.</p>
            <p>And excepted, and forprised out of thys free pardon, all, and singular summe, and summes of money, graunted to the kinges hignesse, or hys most derest father kyng Henry the .viii. by waye, and meane of subsidie, fiftene, beneuolence, loane, contribution, reliefe, or otherwyse, or by any of thesame waies, or meanes: And all deteiners, witholdynges, &amp; none paymentes, touching, or concernyng thesame, or any part thereof: And that the same, or euery part thereof may, and shall by auctoritie aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied, be leuied, taken, and receiued to the kynges vse, any thing in thys free pardone to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And also except, and forprised all wastes of the Kynges wooddes in any of his forrestes, parkes, chases, and elswhere. And also except, and forprised, all, and all maner of wastes committed, or doen in anye of the kinges wardes landes, or in the wardes landes of any committee of the kinges maiestie, or of any of his most noble progenitours committes.</p>
            <p>And also except, and forprised out of this free pardon, all, and euery concealmentes of any custome, or subsidie, and all maner of accomptes and accompt, and all actions, suites, impeticions, and demaundes, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, or concernyng any accomptes, or accompt, &amp; all arrerages of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, and all debtes, impeticions, suites, demaundes, &amp; executions by occasiō, or meanes of any accōpt, which ought to be made to hys hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or to any of hys most noble progenitours. And also excepted &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised all tytles of actions of <hi>Quare impedit,</hi> all rauishmētes, &amp; withol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any of the kinges wardes, or witholding of any wardes lādes, or tenementes, &amp; the profites of the same landes, &amp; tenementes. And all and euery fine, or fines, for the single, or double value of the mariage, or mariages of any of the kinges wardes, at any time growen to the king our souereygne lorde, or to any of hys most noble progenitours.</p>
            <p>And also except, &amp; forprised, all, &amp; singular homages, feaulties, &amp; other seruices, reliefes, rentes, seruices, rentes charges, rētes secke, &amp; tenthes, and the arrerages of euerye of them due to hys highnesse, or to anye of his most noble progenitours. And also except, and forprised out of thys free pardon, all, &amp; singuler forfaitures, &amp; all maner of penalties, summes of money, &amp; profites whatsoeuer growen, or due by reason of any offēce or acte cōmitted, or doen contrary to any statute or statutes, or contrary to the common lawes of this realme, wherof any seasure was made, or anye informacion geuen in anye of the kynges Courtes of Recorde, or
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:184040:33"/> any sute cōmenced, or depēding before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> .xx. day of Ianuary in the third yere of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kynges maiesties reigne, or wherof y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kinges maiestie, or king Henry the .viii. by byll sealed with the seale of any of them, before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied xx. day of Ianuary in the sayed yere of our lord God. M.D. xlix. haue, hath, or shall make any gyft, or assignement to any seruaūtes, or seruaūt of our souereigne lorde the kyng, or of the sayed king Henry the eight, or or to any other persone, or persones.</p>
            <p>And excepte, and forprised out of this free pardone, all, and singular forfaictures, forfaicture, &amp; summe, and summes of money, beyng due to our souereigne lorde the kyng, or to kyng Henry the .vii. or to king Hēry theight, by any penall statute, or statutes, whiche be conuerted into the nature of debt by iudgement, or by agrement of thoffendour.</p>
            <p>And except, and forprised out of this free pardon, all, and all maner of debtes due, &amp; to be due to our souereigne lorde the kyng, or to any of his most noble progenitors, other thē such as are due to our souereigne lord the king, vpon any obligation, or recognisaūce forfaited for none appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or for not keping of the peace, or for not being of good behauour.</p>
            <p>And except, and forprised out of this free pardon, all, and singular fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, aswell fines <hi>pro licētia concordandi,</hi> as other fines for contēptes, or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces set, or taxed. And also all issues, fines, and amerciamētes, aswell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, as other vnder .v. l (other then fines for any alienation, without the kinges lycence) seuerall, or particularly, concerning any one persone, or mo persones ioinctlye, whether the same fines, or amerciamentes before excepted, be totted, or not totted, taken to the charge of anye sheriefe, or sheriefes, or not taken to his, or theyr charge, extreated, or not extreated whether they be turned into debt, or not turned into debt, or not beyng leuied, receiued, or not receiued, by any sheriefe, or sheriefes, baylife, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, or other officer.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwaies and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that this present acte of free pardon, or any thing therein conteined, shal not in any wise extende to discharge, or pardon any offence, peine, or penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, dooen, commytted, or forfaycted, by force of anye estatute heretofore made, against the decaying of any house, or houses of husbandry, or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting of any lande from Tyllage into pasture, otherwise, or in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maner then to pardon, or dyscharge all issues, forfeyctes, peynes; &amp; penalties growen, or due to the kinges maiestie, or to hys late father of most famous memorye kyng Henrye the eyght, before the fyrst daye of Iune, in the yere of our lorde God, a thowsande, fyue hundred &amp; fifty, by reason of any suche offence, or offences, whiche issues, forfaictes, pey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or penalties are playnely, and clearely before pardoned, in, and by this present acte of free pardone, nor shall extende to geue, or make any lycence, or dispensacion to any persone, or persones, to holde, or continue the same so decayed, or conuerted, contrary to the fourme of any estatute or estatutes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184040:34"/>
            <p>Prouyded also, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie of this present par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lpment, that all, and euery persone, and persones, whiche tended to sue liuerie out of the Kynges handes, or that ought to sue any liuerie out of the Kynges handes, or that ought to sue any <hi>Ouster le mayn</hi> of any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, landes, tenementes, or hereditamētes, whatsoeuer they be, shall sue, and be bounden to sue his, or their liuerie, or liueries, and <hi>Ouster le mayn,</hi> of his, or their manours, landes, tenementes, or hereditamentes as they ought, or should haue doen, if this acte of free pardon had neuer been graūted, any article, clause, matter, or sentence, acte, or actes, thing or thinges in this present acte of free pardon comprised, or specified, to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And except, and forprised out of this free pardone, all, and singular persone, and persones, beyng the .xxvi. day of Ianuarye, in the yere of our Lorde God. M.D.xlix. prisoner, or prisoners in the tower of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, in the Flete, in the Mershalsie, or in any other prison, or in any wise by the kynges commaundement, or by the commaundement, or ordre of the Lordes of hys priuie counsaile, restreygned, or stayed from liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie other then suche prisoner, and prisoners, as are in any prison, onely for felonious stealyng of anye gooddes, or Cattalles vnder the summe, and value of .xx.s. so that the same felonious takyng of, &amp; such gooddes, or cattalles, be not feloniously taken, in, or nere anye hygh waye, nor in the dwelling house of any persone in the night time, nor in any churche, or chappell.</p>
            <p>And also except out of this free pardone, all and singular persone, and persones, which at any time before the sayed .xxvi. daye of Ianuarye, in the sayed yere of our Lorde God. M.D.xlix. is, ought, or shalbe put to death, or in execucion by vertue of any maner of iudgemēt against him or them geuen.</p>
            <p>And except, and forprised out of this free pardon, all, and all maner of treasons, doen, cōmitted, or perpetrated by anye persone, or persones, in any of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parties beyond the sea, or in Scotlāde, or by anye persō, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones now being beyond the sea, or in Scotlande, other then such trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, or petit treasons, as haue been commytted, perpetrated, or dooen, by any persone being beyonde the sea, or in Scotlande, that before the feast of thassencion of our lord God, that shalbe in the yere of our lorde God. M.D.L. shall come, and make their returne, and repaire into this realme of Englande. And except and forprised all impetitions, punishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, forfaictures, peynes of death, executions, and iudgementes for the same treasons.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, the kynges Maiestie of hys speciall Grace, and clemencie, is pleased, and contented, that it be enacted, and established by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that all, and singular persone, and persones beyng borne within this Realme of Englande, or in any of the kynges dominions, and now being beyonde the Sea, or in Scotlande, which
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:184040:34"/> before the fyrst day of Nouembre in the yere of our Lorde God, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sande fiue hundred fourtie and nine, did flie out of this Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, or any of the kinges dominions, for any high treason, petit trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, misprision of treason, or for any felonie, or murdre, or other crime, or offence by him, or them committed, in any wise doen, or perpetrated shal by vertue of this free pardon bee clerely discharged, acquited, and pardoned, of all, and all maner of treasons, petit treasones, misprision of treason, or other offences, and crimes whatsoeuer doen, committed, or perpetrated, before thesaied first daie of Nouēbre, in the saied yere of our Lorde God a thousande fiue hundred fourtie, and nine, &amp; of al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of impeticions, sutes, penalties, forfaictures, and executions for the same, So that he, or they do come, and make their retourne, and repaire into this realme of Englande, on thisside thesaied feast of Thassencion of our lorde God, in thesaied yere of our lorde God, M.D.L. And also our saied Souereigne Lord the king by vertue of this acte, and by the aucthorttie abouesaied, doeth geue aucthoritie and licence to all, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of the saied persone, and persons being beyond the sea, or in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, to retourne, and repaire into this realme of England, and other hys dominions before thesame feast of Thassencion of our Lorde God M.D.L.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaied, that it shalbe lawfull to all, and euery clerke, and other officer of anye of the kynges courtes, to whome it apperteineth, without any forfaicture, losse, or punishement for the same, to awarde and make writtes of <hi>Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as vtlegatum,</hi> at the suite of the partie playntife agaynst anye persone, or persones, being outlawed in any action, or sute, to the entent to compell the persone or persones so outlawed, to make aunswere to the plaintife, or plaintifes, at whose sute, he, or they were, or was outlawed. And also that euery persone and persones now being outlawed, shalbe bounden to sue a <hi>Scire facias</hi> against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parties, or parties, at whose suite, he or they were, or was outlawed, or theyr executours, or administratours before such time as the persone, or persones so outlawed shall take any aduaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of thys free pardone, concerning hys, or theyr outlawrye.</p>
            <p>And the king our souereigne lorde is contented, and pleased to graūt by aucthoritie afore sayed, that it shalbe lawfull to all, &amp; singuler Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byshoppes, and byshoppes of thys realme of Englande, and Wales, to deliuer out of prisone, and set at libertie all, and singuler those persones beyng in prisone in theyr custodie, or in the custodie of anye of them, as Clerkes conuicte, or conuicted, whiche be pardoned by this acte of free pardone without any further acte, or suite to be made for allowaunce of thys pardone, or otherwise, any acte of parlament, law, vsage, custome, or other thyng to the contrary, in any wise notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alway, that this acte of generall, and free pardon, or anye thing therin conteyned, extende not to Iohn Wythe of Eylisham in the
<pb facs="tcp:184040:35"/> countie of Norff. any thing in thys acte to the contrary in any wise not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that this acte of free Pardon shall not extende to any persone, or persones, which at any time hertofore haue offended in these heresies, &amp; erronious opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons herafter ensuyng, that is to saye, that infantes ought not to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and if they be baptized, they ought to be rebaptized whē they come to lawfull age. That it is not lefull for a christien man to beare office, or rule in the common wealth. That no mans lawes ought to be obeyed, that it is not leful for a christien man to take an oathe before any Iudge that Christ tooke no bodily substaūce of our blessed ladie: That synners after baptisme cannot be restored by repentaunce. That all thynges be or ought to be common, and nothing seuerall.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwaies, and it is enacted by thaucthoritie aforesaied, that this Acte of free pardon, or any thing therin conteined, shall not in any wyse extende, or be in any wise beneficiall, or take effecte to anye suche persone, or persones, that at any time sythe the feast of Easter last past hath, or haue made any rebellion, or vnlawfull commotion, in any part of thys Realme, or in Wales, whiche at anye tyme syth the .xii. daye of Iune last past, hath, or haue commenced, or sued, and after the last day of February next comming will folow, or continue, or that at any time herafter, shall commence, or sue in propre persone, or by hys, or their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourneye aucthorised, auowe, sue, &amp; folowe, any maner of appeale tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the death of any such rebellious person, or persones, the maiming or beatyng of any of the saied rebellious persone, or persones, or any bill or billes, acciō, or accions of trespasse, or detinue, or action vpon the case agaynst any persone, or persones, that dyd serue the kinges maiestie in, or for the subduyng of the sayed rebellious persones, of, for, or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the taking away, or witholdyng of the goodes, or of Cattalles, any of the sayed rebellious persones, or of, for, or concerning any other acte, or actes personall, doen, or executed in the commoncion time to any of the sayed rebellious persones, by any persone, or persones that serued the king in the commocion time, in the subduing of the same rebellious persones betwene the saied .xii. daye of Iune, and the fyrst day of Nouembre last past.</p>
            <closer>God saue the Kyng.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Richard <hi>Grafton, printer to the</hi> Kynges Maiestie. <hi>1553</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad</hi> impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum solum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184040:35"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>